<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: hiring | Namshi]]></title>
  <link href="http://tech.namshi.com/blog/categories/hiring/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://tech.namshi.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-06-07T01:13:00+04:00</updated>
  <id>http://tech.namshi.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Namshi]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Newsletter #41]]></title>
    <link href="http://tech.namshi.com/blog/2014/06/05/newsletter-number-41/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-05T12:03:00+04:00</updated>
    <id>http://tech.namshi.com/blog/2014/06/05/newsletter-number-41</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Hi fellas, it&rsquo;s #techThursday an here we are with the usual list of interesting topics and resources for the upcoming weekend!</p>

<p>We publish several blog posts in the latest weeks, to be up-to-date just follow us on <a href="http://twitter.com/TechNamshi">twitter</a>.</p>

<p><strong>And you know what? We are hiring!</strong> : ##<strong><a href="http://buff.ly/1pP7x0n">we are looking for a Lead Mobile Developer!</a></strong>##</p>

<ul>
<li><p><a href="http://buff.ly/1pP7x0n">Like Android &amp; iOS? Let&rsquo;s revolutionize shopping in the Middle East! We are hiring a mobile lead developer</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://buff.ly/1nfhXWK">Developers don&rsquo;t write code, they write essays</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://buff.ly/UbTMiq">How We Use Docker To Continuously Deliver Microservices</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://github.com/boot2docker/boot2docker">Boot2Docker: a lightweight Linux distribution made specifically to run Docker containers. Even on you OS X or Windows machine!</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://buff.ly/1h7heav">Meta-programming in JavaScript Using Proxies</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://buff.ly/1ktHCpK">New, Cost-Effective Memory-Optimized DB Instances for Amazon RDS</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://buff.ly/1hJJtqK">PHP 5.6.0beta3 Released</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://buff.ly/RLoUTL">Konzole, a very simple tool to create console apps for #nodejs</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://nondot.org/sabre/">A little of background to how Swift (the new programming language by Apple) development was started</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://github.com/fullstackio/FlappySwift">Swift implementation of flappy bird, on github</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://aosabook.org/en/llvm.html">The LLVM architecture</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://www.trustedreviews.com/opinions/samsung-tizen-os-features">Samsung Tizen OS: 6 Things You Need To Know</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://www.wired.com/2014/06/contiki/">Out in the open: the little-known Open Source OS that rules the Internet of things</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://http://gaudi.io/">Setup of isolated and decoupled dev environments</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://matt.aimonetti.net/posts/2013/08/27/what-technology-should-my-startup-use/">What Technology Should My Startup Use?</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://leanstack.io/categories">Categorized list of great web application/service including companies using it</a></p></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Like Android and iOS? Let's change shopping in the Middle East together!]]></title>
    <link href="http://tech.namshi.com/blog/2014/06/03/like-android-and-ios-lets-change-shopping-in-the-middle-east-together/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-03T16:42:00+04:00</updated>
    <id>http://tech.namshi.com/blog/2014/06/03/like-android-and-ios-lets-change-shopping-in-the-middle-east-together</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Do you like Java? Ok, I possibly started from the wrongest question.</p>

<p>Restart.</p>

<p>Do you like Android? (sounds much better!) And what about iOS? Tablets?
Mobile devices in general? If so, come over and let&rsquo;s change the way
people shop in the Middle East.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>We are looking for a <strong>Lead Mobile Developer</strong>, someone who can get his hands
dirty with both of the main platforms, and teach others how to do it: we&rsquo;d
like you to bring in your expertise and help kicking off our mobile
development team.</p>

<h2>What do we need?</h2>

<p>Our need is to kickoff an internal development team, which could even be split by
iOS and Android, and to do so we would need to make a first, very good hire and
find a lead who can drive all the way to success.</p>

<p>How will your typical day look like? You will go over a <a href="https://gist.github.com">gist</a> which has the specs for
a feature together with the other leads, wrap up a bugfix for the next release,
check one of the pull requests submitted by another team member and have
<a href="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/d/d4/Shawarma_ad_Istanbul_(01.10.2008).JPG">lotsa shawarma</a> for lunch.</p>

<p>As general rules, we would like:</p>

<ul>
<li>someone who speaks both <strong>Android and iOS</strong> (if you know only one of them but think you deserve a position, talk to us and we&rsquo;d be very happy to hear your point)</li>
<li>a few years of proficient <strong>development of mobile applications</strong>, possibly being a leader of a small/mid-sized team</li>
<li>knowledge of the <strong>latest trend</strong> in your technical sector (you tell us if <a href="http://www.omgchrome.com/android-webview-auto-update-future/">android auto-updates its webview component</a>, not the other way round :) as well as suggesting tools like <a href="http://hockeyapp.net/features/">Hockey</a>)</li>
<li><strong>Object-Oriented design</strong>: sounds boring but we don&rsquo;t limit ourselves to MVC, we actually need you to <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/odino/dont-screw-it-up-how-to-build-durable-web-apis-phpday-2014-in-verona-ita">consume our APIs and get the most out of them</a></li>
<li>it would be a plus to get someone who is passionate about <strong>OSS</strong> and would like to release some of our stuff after polishing them for the public</li>
</ul>


<h2>What do we offer?</h2>

<ul>
<li>a good salary, we don&rsquo;t want to hire people who feel they&rsquo;ve been underpaid</li>
<li>SPDY, HTTP APIs and a Service-Oriented Architecture</li>
<li>a <a href="https://www.google.com/maps/dir/First+Gulf+Bank+Metro+Station+1+-+Sheikh+Zayed+Rd+-+Dubai+-+United+Arab+Emirates/More+Cafe+Gold+%26+Diamond+Park+-+Sheikh+Zayed+Rd+-+Dubai+-+United+Arab+Emirates/@25.1264065,55.2068206,18z/data=!3m1!4b1!4m14!4m13!1m5!1m1!1s0x3e5f6bc621973f29:0x18a89384f349bdf6!2m2!1d55.207756!2d25.126699!1m5!1m1!1s0x3e5f6bc6122edfe3:0x435be27ccd3d1564!2m2!1d55.208316!2d25.126114!3e2">1-minute-walk</a> from the metro to the office</li>
<li>a <a href="/team">great team</a></li>
<li>you <strong>will and won&rsquo;t</strong> be alone: our team is made of ~15 software engineers and we share best practices at the architectual / software design level,
but don&rsquo;t have a way to re-invent the current team members into mobile hackers</li>
<li>growth, as mobile is getting bigger and bigger (for us and for the ecommerce market in general): we expect the mobile
development team to be growing as months will go by</li>
<li>a company which is standing on the <a href="http://www.rocket-internet.de/">shoulder of giants</a></li>
<li>the <em>&ldquo;10th our breakpoint&rdquo;</em>: if you work for 10 hours then have a break, order food and we will reimburse it</li>
<li>working with <a href="http://instagram.com/p/gpSOCenpPI/">these two guys</a></li>
</ul>


<h2>So what?</h2>

<p>Simply drop an email at <code>alessandro.nadalin@namshi.com</code> and let&rsquo;s make it real! Need more infos? Check <a href="/join-us">this</a>!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
