<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: hiring | Tech @ Namshi.com]]></title>
  <link href="http://namshi.github.io/blog/categories/hiring/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://namshi.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2018-09-19T11:45:38+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://namshi.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Namshi]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Namshi is hiring: come and hack with us!]]></title>
    <link href="http://namshi.github.io/blog/2018/09/16/namshi-is-hiring-come-and-hack-with-us/"/>
    <updated>2018-09-16T13:27:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://namshi.github.io/blog/2018/09/16/namshi-is-hiring-come-and-hack-with-us</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Looking for a fresh new start in 2019? We might have
the right opening for you!</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>In order to support the growth of our business, we&rsquo;re currently
beefing up our entire tech department, with the intention of
developing even <a href="/blog/2017/05/28/rewriting-the-catalog-api/">faster services</a>
and delivering an even more <a href="http://tech.namshi.io/blog/2018/08/16/improve-our-exchange-process/">amazing customer experience</a>:
the end goal is to re-organize the structure of our team
(which has always been split by skillset, as in &ldquo;mobile&rdquo;, &ldquo;backend&rdquo;, etc)
and mimic the <a href="https://labs.spotify.com/2014/03/27/spotify-engineering-culture-part-1/">squad framework</a>, where technical teams are split
by &ldquo;business function&rdquo;.
We&rsquo;re never going to employ thousands
of engineers but, as we feel the need to build a bigger tech
pipeline and consequently hire additional software engineers,
we think the squad framework provides a good structure for
a bigger organization.</p>

<p>So, lots of hiring coming up here at Namshi: mobile, SRE, frontend, backend&hellip;   &hellip;you name it, we&rsquo;re probably hiring :)</p>

<p>Our mobile team, lead by <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/hannancs112/">Abdul</a>, is playing around with React Native
and works on a daily basis with Swift and the standard
Android toolkit (even though they&rsquo;ve been flirting with
Kotlin every now and then): their mission is to make
our mobile apps blazing fast, smooth and as crash-free as possible.</p>

<p>On the frontend side of things, our team
develops <a href="https://www.thinkwithgoogle.com/intl/en-145/which-brands-have-most-user-friendly-mobile-sites-united-arab-emirates-and-saudi-arabia/">amazing web UXes</a>
and internal tools used within the company: our frontenders
eat React for breakfast and are spearheaded by <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/shidhincr">Shidhin</a>, our
most senior frontend engineer.</p>

<p>On the backend, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/carlesi">Carles</a>
and <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/ayham-alzoubi-06516a52/">Ayham</a>
lead a tight-knit team that focuses on delivering HTTP APIs for
our clients to consume: the team deals with scalability
and performance issues and solve problems that span across the
whole domain, mostly with NodeJS, Python and Go.</p>

<p>Last but not least, our SREs
build infrastructures for more than 100 services, all
deployed through Docker containers orchestrated by
Kubernetes. It is almost unbelievable to see what they
allow others teams to do, especially considering
the team is extremely small, as <a href="/team/#Abdelrahman%20Shiddo">Abdelrahman</a> and
<a href="/team/#Andrey%20Komarov">Andrey</a> are our only SREs.</p>

<p>Sounds interesting enough? Then drop us a line at <em>work-in-tech@namshi.com</em>
and let&rsquo;s have a chat!</p>

<p>Oh, I almost forgot &mdash; a couple more things before leaving:</p>

<ul>
<li>most of our engineers are quite senior, so we&rsquo;d like
to &ldquo;diversify&rdquo; and hire less experienced candidates:
juniors and intermediates are our ideal candidates as
of now. If you consider yourself a senior and would like
to apply, feel free to reach out, as we might be able to
work something out :)</li>
<li>I wrote about our hiring process a while ago but most
of it still stands, so I&rsquo;d recommend you to have a look at
our post &ldquo;<a href="/blog/2016/12/06/get-that-job-at-namshi/">Get that job at Namshi</a>&rdquo;</li>
</ul>


<p>Adios!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Currently hiring: a CyberSecurity engineer]]></title>
    <link href="http://namshi.github.io/blog/2018/07/04/currently-hiring-a-cybersecurity-engineer/"/>
    <updated>2018-07-04T06:28:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://namshi.github.io/blog/2018/07/04/currently-hiring-a-cybersecurity-engineer</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Love penetration testing, DefCon, bug bounty programs and scrapping through lines
of code to find vulnerabilities? Then we might have the right opening for you!</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Here at Namshi we&rsquo;re committed to continuously improve our security posture, by
either <a href="/blog/2018/05/16/introducing-the-namshi-bug-bounty-program/">collaborating with security researchers across the globe</a> or with in-house expertise.</p>

<p>With this in mind, we would like to hire a security researcher that can help
us from this perspective: we see security as being a topic that will only gain additional
importance as time goes by, and we&rsquo;re committed to dedicating the right amount of time,
and money, to the cause :)</p>

<p>As a <strong>Security Engineer</strong>, you&rsquo;ll be tasked with running internal assessments, ranging
from <em>pentesting</em> our cloud infrastructure to social engineering around the office,
review our security policies and define the best strategy to improve our posture.
In addition to that, you will be actively collaborating with external researchers
through our HackerOne program, which is going to be directly under your responsibility.
On top of this, as the months will go by, you will probably spend time training
both our technical and non-technical staff to raise awareness and make sure we
got the basics covered.</p>

<p>Been into it since Kali was Backtrack? Spend time going through public bounty programs
to hack your way to a reward? Want to take on the responsibility of shaping Namshi&rsquo;s
defense? Then we’re definitely a match!</p>

<h2>Apply now!</h2>

<p>What are you waiting for? Send your application to <code>work-in-tech@namshi.com</code> and
let&rsquo;s have a chat!</p>

<p>P.S. A few months back I wrote a small piece about <a href="/blog/2016/12/06/get-that-job-at-namshi/">Namshi&rsquo;s hiring process and <em>desiderata</em></a>,
give it a look!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Currently hiring: sr. backend engineers]]></title>
    <link href="http://namshi.github.io/blog/2018/07/03/currently-hiring-sr-backend-engineers/"/>
    <updated>2018-07-03T08:52:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://namshi.github.io/blog/2018/07/03/currently-hiring-sr-backend-engineers</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Love microservices, NodeJS and distributed systems? Then we might have the right
opening for you!</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Here at Namshi we&rsquo;re constantly trying to renovate our stack by using the best
from the open source ecosystem: from <a href="https://nodejs.org/en/">NodeJS</a> to <a href="https://kubernetes.io/">Kubernetes</a>, our stack bleeds with
interesting tools to work with.</p>

<p>As a Sr. Backend Engineer, you&rsquo;ll be tasked to work on a spectrum of services
ranging from our customer-facing APIs to tools that power our logistics infrastructure.
We are a very pragmatic and experienced team, so from time to time you will see
engineers busy TDDing on a feature, whereas other times we&rsquo;re <em>straight to live</em>.
We pride of being a heterogeneous team that&rsquo;s experienced to know how and when to
abstract.</p>

<p>We run a Service-Oriented architecture with 100+ microservices where JS plays a
huge part: <a href="https://stackshare.io/namshi">our stack is comprised of many different tools</a>
and we&rsquo;re always up to experimenting in light of new, harder challenges.</p>

<p>Some of the things our backend team has been working over the past few months:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="/blog/2017/05/28/rewriting-the-catalog-api/">rewriting one of our most sensitive APIs</a>, bringing the median response time down to 30ms</li>
<li>moving <a href="/blog/2017/02/06/towards-high-availability-and-beyond/">wonky pieces of our infrastructure</a> towards high-availability</li>
<li>releasing some interesting open-source <a href="https://github.com/namshi/stackdriver-pushgateway">backend bits</a></li>
</ul>


<p>Most of our backend apps are built with NodeJS, although some of the apps
still kick it in Symfony2 or pythonic boots. With a fleet of 100+ microservices, we&rsquo;re
generally very busy trying to innovate as much as possible &mdash; and refactoring when
we need to pay our technical debt back.</p>

<p>Understand the HTTP protocol? Like deploying microservices on kubernetes? Async
programming doesn&rsquo;t scare you? Then we&rsquo;re definitely a match!</p>

<h2>Apply now!</h2>

<p>What are you waiting for? Send your application to <code>work-in-tech@namshi.com</code> and
let&rsquo;s have a chat!</p>

<p>P.S. A few months back I wrote a small piece about <a href="/blog/2016/12/06/get-that-job-at-namshi/">Namshi&rsquo;s hiring process and <em>desiderata</em></a>,
give it a look!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Currently hiring: a frontend engineer]]></title>
    <link href="http://namshi.github.io/blog/2018/01/07/currently-hiring-a-frontend-engineer/"/>
    <updated>2018-01-07T12:07:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://namshi.github.io/blog/2018/01/07/currently-hiring-a-frontend-engineer</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Love React, React Native, the dom and webperf? Then we might have the right
opening for you!</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>It is no news that we&rsquo;ve been banking on the JS ecosystem
for a few years: from rolling out our first angular apps in 2013 to using React
Native in our android app, we&rsquo;ve been very busy trying to push our frontends
as far as possible.</p>

<p>We run a Service-Oriented architecture where JS plays a huge part: most of our
services are either SPAs or small NodeJS-backed APIs, and <strong>JavaScript is king</strong> at
Namshi.</p>

<p>We would like to work with someone who has a very strong background in the language,
who&rsquo;s been battling on the frontend for a few years and is not afraid to dive into
Node, if required.</p>

<p>Some of the things our frontend team has been working over the past few months:</p>

<ul>
<li>integrating React Native on our <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.namshi.android">android app</a></li>
<li><a href="/blog/2017/05/02/rebuilding-our-mobile-website/">improving conversion rate on our mobile website by 20%</a></li>
<li>releasing some interesting open-sourced <a href="https://github.com/namshi/slim-slider">frontend</a> <a href="https://github.com/namshi/dollar-dom">bits</a></li>
</ul>


<p>Most of our frontend apps are built with React, although some of the older apps
still kick it in angular boots. With a fleet of 100+ microservices, we&rsquo;re
generally very busy trying to innovate as much as possible.</p>

<p>Understand the inner workings of virtual dom? Think redux is not a replacement
for components' state? Grasp how HTTP/2 helps frontend developers?
Then we&rsquo;re definitely a match!</p>

<h2>Apply now!</h2>

<p>What are you waiting for? Send your application at <code>work-in-tech@namshi.com</code> and
let&rsquo;s have a chat!</p>

<p>P.S. A few weeks back I wrote a small piece about <a href="/blog/2016/12/06/get-that-job-at-namshi/">Namshi&rsquo;s hiring process and <em>desiderata</em></a>,
give it a look!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Currently hiring: backend and mobile engineers]]></title>
    <link href="http://namshi.github.io/blog/2017/03/09/currently-hiring-backend-mobile-developers-dubai/"/>
    <updated>2017-03-09T06:49:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://namshi.github.io/blog/2017/03/09/currently-hiring-backend-mobile-developers-dubai</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We&rsquo;re currently looking for some help in a couple areas of our tech team &mdash; why
don&rsquo;t <strong>you</strong> join us?</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Mobile</h2>

<p>Getting into the specifics, we&rsquo;ve been working with an external mobile team (3rd party)
that wrote our apps from scratch, setup an efficient testing &amp; CI strategy and a
very solid deployment workflow &mdash; as a matter of fact, we&rsquo;re very proud of our
crash rate on both platforms, with android leading at 0.05%.</p>

<p>We are comfortable with the quality of our apps and the pace of development but,
in order to take them to the next level, it&rsquo;s clear to us that we need our own
team to do that: commitment, communication and going the extra-mile are definitely
different when you&rsquo;re part of the organization.</p>

<p>On the long run the team is going to be comprised of a few engineers and a lead,
so we&rsquo;d initially like to start with:</p>

<ul>
<li>1 <strong>lead mobile developer</strong>, who should ideally have good experience on both platforms</li>
<li>1 <strong>senior iOS developer</strong></li>
<li>1 <strong>senior android developer</strong></li>
</ul>


<p>The <strong>lead mobile engineer</strong> should ideally be a very hands-on, seasoned mobile
engineer with experience leading / forming a team &mdash; he will need to
help building the team, setting the right direction, overseeing development
on both platforms and coordinating with other teams (ie. backend
or product management) on feature development and aligning priorities. We expect
him to spend around 50% of his time on development (this is still a <em>hands-on</em> position),
and the other 50% on the team, teaching practices, reviewing pull requests and so on.</p>

<p>We expect from <strong>senior engineers</strong> to be able to write clean, testable code that&rsquo;s
hard to break &mdash; a few years (4+) of experience are definitely needed (say, you
should have bumped into <code>@autoreleasepool</code> before ;&ndash;)) and you
should be very familiar with different design patterns (Delegate, Facade, etc),
concepts such as mock objects and various tools to support your workflow (ie. CI
pipelines).</p>

<h2>Backend</h2>

<p>We could definitely use some help in our backend team :)</p>

<p>Even though we&rsquo;re not in a rough spot, we would like to be able to expand
our pipeline and be able to add even more seniority to the team: our usual &ldquo;backend problem&rdquo;
is that we have lots of things we&rsquo;d like to work on / experiment with but not a lot
of engineers, thus we eventually end up giving those projects up or delaying them
too much.</p>

<p>The main technologies you would be working with are:</p>

<ul>
<li>NodeJS</li>
<li>MySQL</li>
<li>Redis</li>
<li>Solr</li>
<li>Golang</li>
<li>Symfony2</li>
<li>a bit of frontend with either Angular or React</li>
</ul>


<p>all of these in the context of our microservice-based SOA: we currently employ
50+ service in production, mostly deployed in Docker containers through Google&rsquo;s
<a href="https://kubernetes.io/">Kubernetes</a>.</p>

<p>Here we would keep in consideration candidates for both a <strong>lead</strong> and a
<strong>senior</strong> position: the current team is working well and we haven&rsquo;t felt the
need to hire a lead engineer over the past few months, but we&rsquo;re open to the
idea if we find the right candidate.</p>

<p>Needless to say, both position would be <strong>quite hands-on</strong> :)</p>

<h2>Apply now!</h2>

<p>What are you waiting for? Send your application at <code>work-in-tech@namshi.com</code> and
let&rsquo;s have a chat!</p>

<p>P.S. A few weeks back I wrote a small piece about <a href="http://tech.namshi.io/blog/2016/12/06/get-that-job-at-namshi/">Namshi&rsquo;s hiring process and <em>desiderata</em></a>,
give it a look!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
