<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: hiring | Tech @ Namshi.com]]></title>
  <link href="http://namshi.github.io/blog/categories/hiring/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://namshi.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2018-01-07T12:20:22+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://namshi.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Namshi]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Currently hiring: a frontend engineer]]></title>
    <link href="http://namshi.github.io/blog/2018/01/07/currently-hiring-a-frontend-engineer/"/>
    <updated>2018-01-07T12:07:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://namshi.github.io/blog/2018/01/07/currently-hiring-a-frontend-engineer</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Love React, React Native, the dom and webperf? Then we might have the right
opening for you!</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>It is no news that we&rsquo;ve been banking on the JS ecosystem
for a few years: from rolling out our first angular apps in 2013 to using React
Native in our android app, we&rsquo;ve been very busy trying to push our frontends
as far as possible.</p>

<p>We run a Service-Oriented architecture where JS plays a huge part: most of our
services are either SPAs or small NodeJS-backed APIs, and <strong>JavaScript is king</strong> at
Namshi.</p>

<p>We would like to work with someone who has a very strong background in the language,
who&rsquo;s been battling on the frontend for a few years and is not afraid to dive into
Node, if required.</p>

<p>Some of the things our frontend team has been working over the past few months:</p>

<ul>
<li>integrating React Native on our <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.namshi.android">android app</a></li>
<li><a href="/blog/2017/05/02/rebuilding-our-mobile-website/">improving conversion rate on our mobile website by 20%</a></li>
<li>releasing some interesting open-sourced <a href="https://github.com/namshi/slim-slider">frontend</a> <a href="https://github.com/namshi/dollar-dom">bits</a></li>
</ul>


<p>Most of our frontend apps are built with React, although some of the older apps
still kick it in angular boots. With a fleet of 100+ microservices, we&rsquo;re
generally very busy trying to innovate as much as possible.</p>

<p>Understand the inner workings of virtual dom? Think redux is not a replacement
for components' state? Grasp how HTTP/2 helps frontend developers?
Then we&rsquo;re definitely a match!</p>

<h2>Apply now!</h2>

<p>What are you waiting for? Send your application at <code>work-in-tech@namshi.com</code> and
let&rsquo;s have a chat!</p>

<p>P.S. A few weeks back I wrote a small piece about <a href="/blog/2016/12/06/get-that-job-at-namshi/">Namshi&rsquo;s hiring process and <em>desiderata</em></a>,
give it a look!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Currently hiring: backend and mobile engineers]]></title>
    <link href="http://namshi.github.io/blog/2017/03/09/currently-hiring-backend-mobile-developers-dubai/"/>
    <updated>2017-03-09T06:49:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://namshi.github.io/blog/2017/03/09/currently-hiring-backend-mobile-developers-dubai</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We&rsquo;re currently looking for some help in a couple areas of our tech team &mdash; why
don&rsquo;t <strong>you</strong> join us?</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Mobile</h2>

<p>Getting into the specifics, we&rsquo;ve been working with an external mobile team (3rd party)
that wrote our apps from scratch, setup an efficient testing &amp; CI strategy and a
very solid deployment workflow &mdash; as a matter of fact, we&rsquo;re very proud of our
crash rate on both platforms, with android leading at 0.05%.</p>

<p>We are comfortable with the quality of our apps and the pace of development but,
in order to take them to the next level, it&rsquo;s clear to us that we need our own
team to do that: commitment, communication and going the extra-mile are definitely
different when you&rsquo;re part of the organization.</p>

<p>On the long run the team is going to be comprised of a few engineers and a lead,
so we&rsquo;d initially like to start with:</p>

<ul>
<li>1 <strong>lead mobile developer</strong>, who should ideally have good experience on both platforms</li>
<li>1 <strong>senior iOS developer</strong></li>
<li>1 <strong>senior android developer</strong></li>
</ul>


<p>The <strong>lead mobile engineer</strong> should ideally be a very hands-on, seasoned mobile
engineer with experience leading / forming a team &mdash; he will need to
help building the team, setting the right direction, overseeing development
on both platforms and coordinating with other teams (ie. backend
or product management) on feature development and aligning priorities. We expect
him to spend around 50% of his time on development (this is still a <em>hands-on</em> position),
and the other 50% on the team, teaching practices, reviewing pull requests and so on.</p>

<p>We expect from <strong>senior engineers</strong> to be able to write clean, testable code that&rsquo;s
hard to break &mdash; a few years (4+) of experience are definitely needed (say, you
should have bumped into <code>@autoreleasepool</code> before ;&ndash;)) and you
should be very familiar with different design patterns (Delegate, Facade, etc),
concepts such as mock objects and various tools to support your workflow (ie. CI
pipelines).</p>

<h2>Backend</h2>

<p>We could definitely use some help in our backend team :)</p>

<p>Even though we&rsquo;re not in a rough spot, we would like to be able to expand
our pipeline and be able to add even more seniority to the team: our usual &ldquo;backend problem&rdquo;
is that we have lots of things we&rsquo;d like to work on / experiment with but not a lot
of engineers, thus we eventually end up giving those projects up or delaying them
too much.</p>

<p>The main technologies you would be working with are:</p>

<ul>
<li>NodeJS</li>
<li>MySQL</li>
<li>Redis</li>
<li>Solr</li>
<li>Golang</li>
<li>Symfony2</li>
<li>a bit of frontend with either Angular or React</li>
</ul>


<p>all of these in the context of our microservice-based SOA: we currently employ
50+ service in production, mostly deployed in Docker containers through Google&rsquo;s
<a href="https://kubernetes.io/">Kubernetes</a>.</p>

<p>Here we would keep in consideration candidates for both a <strong>lead</strong> and a
<strong>senior</strong> position: the current team is working well and we haven&rsquo;t felt the
need to hire a lead engineer over the past few months, but we&rsquo;re open to the
idea if we find the right candidate.</p>

<p>Needless to say, both position would be <strong>quite hands-on</strong> :)</p>

<h2>Apply now!</h2>

<p>What are you waiting for? Send your application at <code>work-in-tech@namshi.com</code> and
let&rsquo;s have a chat!</p>

<p>P.S. A few weeks back I wrote a small piece about <a href="http://tech.namshi.io/blog/2016/12/06/get-that-job-at-namshi/">Namshi&rsquo;s hiring process and <em>desiderata</em></a>,
give it a look!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Currently hiring: a DevOps engineer and a JS hacker here in Dubai]]></title>
    <link href="http://namshi.github.io/blog/2016/08/07/currently-hiring-a-devops-engineer-and-a-js-hacker-here-in-dubai/"/>
    <updated>2016-08-07T11:29:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://namshi.github.io/blog/2016/08/07/currently-hiring-a-devops-engineer-and-a-js-hacker-here-in-dubai</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Hey folks, here at <a href="https://www.namshi.com">Namshi</a> we&rsquo;re currently looking
to beef our team up &mdash; without further ado, let me quickly go through both
of them!</p>

<!-- more -->


<ul>
<li><p><strong>Sr. DevOps engineer</strong>: we run our entire stack on AWS, and 99% of our
services run in Docker containers orchestrated via <a href="http://kubernetes.io/">Kubernetes</a>:
a big chunk of our infrastructure is provisioned through <a href="https://saltstack.com/">SaltStack</a>
and we like to keep things simple, reliable and robust &mdash; inspired by
<a href="https://www.infoq.com/news/2013/05/dystopia-as-a-service">Netflix&rsquo;s dystopian architecture</a>.
We believe in fault-tolerant, reactive architectures that don&rsquo;t care about a
server going down, as others will be able to take on the load, or automated checks
will make sure new HW comes online &mdash; and that&rsquo;s how we setup our live infrastructure,
where a sizable chunk of our services runs through spot instances, with confidence :)
We are now looking for someone who can help us lifting the team a step further, playing
with tools like:</p>

<ul>
<li>golang / python / bash</li>
<li>Docker</li>
<li>Kubernets / Swarm / Mesos</li>
<li>AWS</li>
<li>SaltStack / Ansible / Chef</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<p>In the past 18 months we&rsquo;ve worked on a few interesting challenges such as:</p>

<ul>
<li>implementing ChatOps</li>
<li>utilizing containers on our live infrastructure</li>
<li>integrating Terraform to automate tasks / provisioning</li>
<li>reduced our AWS bill, while growing as a company, by writing more efficient
applications and introducing spot instances in our fleet</li>
</ul>


<p>This gives you an overview of the kind of stuff we would love you to work on:
we think of DevOps engineers as a mix between software developers
and system administrators, so we&rsquo;d like you to know a bit of both :)</p>

<ul>
<li><p><strong>(Sr.) JS engineer</strong>: it is no news that we&rsquo;ve been exploring the JS ecosystem
for a few years now: from rolling out our first angular apps in 2013 to testing
React Native in the past months, we&rsquo;ve been very busy trying to push our frontends
as far as possible.
We run a Service-Oriented architecture where JS plays a huge part: most of our
services are either SPAs or small NodeJS-backed APIs, and JavaScript is king at
Namshi.
We would like to work with someone who has a very strong background in the language,
who&rsquo;s been battling on the frontend for a few years and is not afraid to dive into
Node, if required.
Some of the things our frontend team has been working over the past few weeks:</p>

<ul>
<li>React Native</li>
<li>Redux</li>
<li>MobX</li>
<li>isomorphic JavaScript</li>
<li>AMP</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<p>Most of our frontend apps are built with Angular, although we&rsquo;re heavily experimenting
with React, even for our internal tools. With a fleet of 50+ microservices, we&rsquo;re
generally very busy trying to innovate as much as possible.</p>

<p>We&rsquo;re open to very promising, junior candidates even though we&rsquo;re currently hoping
to find someone with a few years of experience on his / her back &mdash; if you feel you
do not have the experience but have the right attitude, then let&rsquo;s definitely have
a chat.</p>

<p>What are you waiting for? Drop a line at <code>work-in-tech@namshi.com</code> and let&rsquo;s
start this journey together!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[We're hiring backend-ers!]]></title>
    <link href="http://namshi.github.io/blog/2016/01/18/were-hiring-backend-ers/"/>
    <updated>2016-01-18T19:26:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://namshi.github.io/blog/2016/01/18/were-hiring-backend-ers</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>2016 has come&hellip;   &hellip;time for new entries in the
<a href="/team">tech team</a>: what&rsquo;s better, to start the year
off, than new faces working on a <a href="http://martinfowler.com/articles/microservices.html">microservice-based SOA</a>
mostly powered by <a href="https://nodejs.org/en/">NodeJS</a> running
through <a href="https://www.docker.com/">Docker</a> containers?</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Namshi is looking to beef its backend team up, with
solid engineers who can think of great solutions to
implement small, isolated, fault tolerant microservices
in our architecture: people who strive to write clean
code but also see the point of being pragmatic, who
know how to write automated tests but also know <em>when</em>
they might not be needed, who know when to abstract and
when too much abstraction is detrimental, who&hellip;
&hellip;well, you got the drill!</p>

<p>We mostly code in JavaScript, both on the frontend and
the backend, but, if you never got the chance to work with
it, don&rsquo;t worry: we believe that with the right mindset the
language won&rsquo;t matter that much &mdash; in fact, these are a few
things we care about, and they&rsquo;re not platform-specific:</p>

<ul>
<li>you have designed and mantained HTTP APIs before</li>
<li>know how to build fault-tolerance services that can run in high-availability setups</li>
<li>crunch on DRY, KISS and YAGNI (<a href="http://www.itexico.com/blog/bid/99765/Software-Development-KISS-YAGNI-DRY-3-Principles-to-simplify-your-life">whaaaat?</a>)</li>
<li>you are a detail-oriented, result-driven individual and are looking to grow in a multi-faceted environment</li>
<li>allergic to monolithic architectures is a plus</li>
</ul>


<p>We love to innovate and try to always follow the latest
trends in Web development &mdash; here are some of the things
we did over the past couple of years:</p>

<ul>
<li>developed <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/unlucio/back-to-the-future-isomorphic-javascript-applications">isomorphic JavaScript apps</a></li>
<li>deployed a fleet of <a href="https://www.docker.com/">containers</a> through <a href="http://kubernetes.io/">Kubernetes</a></li>
<li>been on the frontline to adopt SPDY &mdash; now it&rsquo;s time to switch to HTTP/2</li>
<li>have spent a substantial amount of time trying to help the <a href="https://github.com/namshi">Open Source community</a></li>
</ul>


<p>Now we&rsquo;re playing around with React Native and Redux to see
if JavaScript could conquer the mobile apps landscape.</p>

<p>Our core team is based in Dubai but we&rsquo;re open to remote
candidates: you can find more about us by having a look
at our <a href="https://github.com/namshi">open source libraries</a> or
scraping our <a href="http://tech.namshi.io">tech blog</a>.</p>

<p>If you think you could <a href="http://tech.namshi.io/join-us/">fit into the team</a>, drop us a line
at <em>work-in-tech@namshi.com</em> and let&rsquo;s make it happen!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[We're hiring...actually, we're hiring MOAR!]]></title>
    <link href="http://namshi.github.io/blog/2014/08/13/were-hiring-dot-dot-dot-actually-were-hiring-moar/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-13T12:14:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://namshi.github.io/blog/2014/08/13/were-hiring-dot-dot-dot-actually-were-hiring-moar</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Just an heads up that we are looking for talented
engineers for our tech team, and our guys are very
sad they don&rsquo;t have too many new friends!</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Besides looking for a Lead Mobile developer, as we
<a href="/blog/2014/06/03/like-android-and-ios-lets-change-shopping-in-the-middle-east-together/">announced a few weeks back</a>,
we are looking for some other key figures in our team.</p>

<h2>No HTML/CSS love&hellip;</h2>

<p>Our frontend team, usually happy to write AngularJS
directives or a bunch of frontend-ish NodeJS apps,
is devastated as they feel they are missing a third
element who can help them achieve greatness.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/frontend-sad.png"></p>

<p>To make Lucio and Shidhin happy, we want to add a new
member in our team, a <strong>Frontend Developer</strong>, someone who
is skilled on HTML5 and CSS3 and knows the basics of
JavaScript but wants to expand his knowledge in that
direction.</p>

<p>You will work on a whole lot of new internal applications
as well as help streamlining our frontend processes, together
with the rest of the team: which frameworks shall we use? Bootstrap or
Foundation? How can we use Yeoman&rsquo;s generator to speed up
most of our code generation? How can we make our web apps
faster <a href="https://github.com/addyosmani/critical">extracting critical styles</a>
and so on? These are just a few questions you will need to
ask yourself once you come here.</p>

<p>You will come here knowing how to design a frontend (mastering
the presentation layer, so HTML, CSS, jQuery) but will leave Namshi
knowing how to build the presentation and logic behind a full
frontend application (AngularJS, Node or something more spicy
like <a href="http://www.polymer-project.org/">polymer</a>).</p>

<blockquote><p>Drop us an email at <a href="&#109;&#97;&#x69;&#108;&#x74;&#111;&#58;&#x77;&#x6f;&#x72;&#107;&#45;&#x69;&#x6e;&#x2d;&#x74;&#101;&#x63;&#104;&#64;&#110;&#97;&#109;&#x73;&#104;&#x69;&#46;&#99;&#x6f;&#x6d;">&#119;&#x6f;&#x72;&#107;&#x2d;&#105;&#110;&#x2d;&#x74;&#101;&#99;&#x68;&#64;&#x6e;&#97;&#x6d;&#115;&#104;&#105;&#46;&#99;&#x6f;&#109;</a> to apply or simply
get more informations about this job opening!</p></blockquote>

<h2>Sitting on an empty (sysadmin) chair&hellip;</h2>

<p>Look at the systeam, so sad: they really
need some new buddy for their games.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/sys-sad.png"></p>

<p>The chair is empty, and that makes me so sad! If only
we could find someone who would like to come and join
the hottest SOA of the Middle East&hellip;</p>

<p>So yeah, we&rsquo;re also looking for a <strong>System Administrator</strong>,
someone who knows how configuration management works,
who has relevant experience on cloud infrastructures as
AWS and wants to use some of the latest technologies, like
Docker or Deis, to help us automate and scale the hell out
of our architecture; we are trying to switch towards a more
devops oriented organization, and need someone with that
mindset to improve the current state of the team: as an example,
we use <a href="http://serverspec.org/">serverspec</a> to test some of
our configurations, and would like someone who can get his/her
hands dirty with both programming and system administration
to help the team.</p>

<blockquote><p>Drop us an email at <a href="&#x6d;&#97;&#105;&#108;&#116;&#x6f;&#x3a;&#x77;&#x6f;&#114;&#107;&#x2d;&#x69;&#110;&#45;&#116;&#x65;&#99;&#x68;&#64;&#110;&#97;&#109;&#115;&#x68;&#105;&#46;&#x63;&#x6f;&#x6d;">&#119;&#111;&#114;&#107;&#45;&#105;&#x6e;&#45;&#116;&#x65;&#99;&#104;&#64;&#110;&#x61;&#109;&#115;&#104;&#105;&#x2e;&#x63;&#x6f;&#109;</a> to apply or simply
get more informations about this job opening!</p></blockquote>

<h2>I don&rsquo;t know if he&rsquo;s crying because of loneliness or because of NodeJS&hellip;</h2>

<p>Look at how sad Cirpo, our lead API engineer, was
today:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/cirpo-sad.png"></p>

<p>It&rsquo;s true that he might be sad because we decided
to use a lot of NodeJS instead of PHP, but I
think his struggles also come from the fact that he feels
we need a good <strong>Senior Software engineer</strong>, specialized in
NodeJS, who can help the team getting more skilled with
this &ldquo;new&rdquo; platform.</p>

<p>The ideal candidate would have a few years of experience
on production-ready Node systems, and it would be a great
plus if we can get someone who has a broader experience
with different programming paradigms, as we feel the most
important part of this job is the brain, and it would be great
if we get someone that has been in a few different battlefields :)</p>

<p>We need someone who first solves the problem, then writes the
code (or, even better: first solves the problem, then writes the
test, then the code :-D).</p>

<blockquote><p>Drop us an email at <a href="&#x6d;&#x61;&#x69;&#108;&#x74;&#111;&#x3a;&#x77;&#111;&#x72;&#x6b;&#x2d;&#x69;&#x6e;&#45;&#x74;&#x65;&#x63;&#104;&#64;&#110;&#97;&#x6d;&#115;&#104;&#x69;&#x2e;&#99;&#111;&#109;">&#119;&#111;&#x72;&#x6b;&#45;&#105;&#x6e;&#x2d;&#x74;&#101;&#99;&#104;&#x40;&#x6e;&#97;&#x6d;&#x73;&#x68;&#x69;&#x2e;&#x63;&#x6f;&#x6d;</a> to apply or simply
get more informations about this job opening!</p></blockquote>

<h2>About Namshi</h2>

<p>We have a <a href="/join-us">JOIN US</a> page where we listed some of the key
benefits in working with us, but to recap the most important ones:</p>

<ul>
<li>the environment is great, young and people are passionate</li>
<li>the office is 1 minute away from the metro station</li>
<li>we offer competitive salaries</li>
<li>flexible working hours</li>
<li>being paid to write <a href="https://github.com/namshi">Open Source code</a></li>
<li>cakes! cakes! cakes!</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
