<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: BigQuery | Tech @ Namshi.com]]></title>
  <link href="http://namshi.github.io/blog/categories/bigquery/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://namshi.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2019-09-10T12:39:27+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://namshi.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Namshi]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Syncing millions of records a day to BigQuery: our experience moving from GAE to GKE]]></title>
    <link href="http://namshi.github.io/blog/2018/09/25/syncing-millions-of-records-a-day-to-bigquery-our-experience-moving-from-gae-to-gke/"/>
    <updated>2018-09-25T20:59:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://namshi.github.io/blog/2018/09/25/syncing-millions-of-records-a-day-to-bigquery-our-experience-moving-from-gae-to-gke</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This week we moved one of our analytics workloads from
<a href="https://cloud.google.com/appengine/">Google App Engine</a> (GAE) to the <a href="https://cloud.google.com/kubernetes-engine/">Google Kubernetes Engine</a>
(GKE), and wanted to share our experience in simplifying
a setup that syncs millions of records to BigQuery each
and every day.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Prelude</h2>

<p>At Namshi, we run all kinds of workloads, from internal apps
used by some of our departments to customer-facing APIs.</p>

<p>Recently, we&rsquo;ve come up with a particular challenge: we
wanted to track a high volume of events that happen on our
mobile applications, and our go-to choice was to rely on
<a href="https://tagmanager.google.com">Google Tag Manager</a> to send these events to <a href="https://analytics.google.com">Google Analytics</a>.</p>

<p>Long story short, the events we&rsquo;re trying to track
aren&rsquo;t your usual pageview, or click on a product
page, but a more casual action users do while browsing
our apps &mdash; around 30M of them on a slow day. As soon
as we started sending this additional traffic over,
GA started rate-limiting us and it became clear
we wouldn&rsquo;t be able to piggy-back on
Google&rsquo;s analytics offering for this kind of tracking.</p>

<p>The next natural solution was to build our own event
collector, something that proved to be extremely
interesting: even though we&rsquo;re not going to dig deep
into our code (it&rsquo;s really not that crazy!) we believe
the experience taught us a lot.</p>

<h2>Architecture</h2>

<p>As soon as we decided to build our own collector,
we were faced with 2 simple questions: <strong>where</strong> to
store this data and <strong>what platform</strong> to use?</p>

<p>To begin with, we benchmarked <a href="https://bigquery.cloud.google.com/">BigQuery</a>&rsquo;s <a href="https://cloud.google.com/bigquery/streaming-data-into-bigquery">streaming
protocol</a> and found it could easily sustain the
amount of data we wanted to transfer so,
considering we&rsquo;re pretty well versed with BigQuery as
we use it for a plethora of other projects,
this was a quick and easy decision.</p>

<p>Then it came the time to decide on which
platform we would build the app itself,
and this was, again, a fairly easy decision:
what we were looking for was a fast, pragmatic
platform that would allows us to build
high-performance webservers and integrate
with BQ seamlessly. Our choice was Golang,
as it allows to build incredibly efficient
servers and has a very well-built
<a href="https://godoc.org/cloud.google.com/go/bigquery">package to interface directly with BigQuery</a>.</p>

<p>As I mentioned, our code was fairly simple:
a request comes in, we pull parameters from
the URL and sync it into BigQuery.</p>

<p>``` go
// Code is simplified as our full codebase
// does things you don&rsquo;t really need to get into&hellip; ;)
type Event struct {</p>

<pre><code>Data string
Ts   time.Time
</code></pre>

<p>}</p>

<p>http.HandleFunc(&ldquo;/track-me&rdquo;, func(w http.ResponseWriter, req *http.Request) {</p>

<pre><code>client, err := bigquery.NewClient(ctx, PROJECT_ID)
if err != nil {
    // ...handle error...
}
u := client.Dataset(DATASET).Table(TABLE).Uploader()

events := []*Event{
    {Data: req.URL.Query(), Ts: time.Now()},
}
if err := u.Put(ctx, events); err != nil {
    log.Printf("error: %s", err)
}

io.WriteString(w, "ok")
</code></pre>

<p>})
```</p>

<p>Now, the app is definitely not optimized, as it tries
to sync to BigQuery at every request &mdash; which is a
(fairly) expensive operation: we had a reason for keeping
it this way, a reason called Google App Engine.</p>

<h2>On GAE</h2>

<p>Since we were worried about the scalability of our
hosting platform, we decided
to deploy this application on Google App Engine,
an infinitely scalable platform ran by Google.</p>

<p>The tricky bit of GAE is that it &ldquo;forces&rdquo;
you to run all of your application logic <a href="https://stackoverflow.com/questions/149307/background-tasks-on-app-engine">within
a single request/response</a>:
everything you want to do needs to be completed
before you return a response to the client.
This is definitely an acceptable trade-off in
a lot of use-cases, as it guarantees that Google
can spin instances up and down at will, but didn&rsquo;t
work too great for us as it really added an expensive
operation in our route (syncing to BigQuery).</p>

<p>Ideally, we would have liked to be able to execute the
sync in background, but App Engine has a fairly <a href="https://cloud.google.com/appengine/docs/standard/python/taskqueue/">complex
implementation of background jobs</a> that we didn&rsquo;t like
as much, as we wanted to keep the setup as simple
as possible.</p>

<p>We went live with a working app within a day,
but we immediately noticed a problem, as latency was
much higher than we expected:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/gae-latency.png"></p>

<p>A median of 300ms for an app that simply receives a request
and syncs it to BigQuery seemed way higher than
we expected: we eventually didn&rsquo;t bother as much
as what we needed wasn&rsquo;t high-performance, but rather
high-scalability, and GAE fit the bill perfectly.</p>

<p>After a couple weeks, though, we noticed another
interesting problem: since the app wasn&rsquo;t as
efficient as we thought, lots of GAE instances
were being used to keep up with the amount of traffic
we were receiving, something that reflected on
our GCP bill right away:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/gae-price.png"></p>

<p>This little tracking app was costing us around
$150 a day ($4500 per month), way more than we initially budgeted:
time to review the setup and come up with
a more efficient way to use Google&rsquo;s servers,
at a fraction of the cost.</p>

<h2>GKE</h2>

<p>We are very big on Kubernetes, so the very next step
was to try to move our application to the GKE,
Google&rsquo;s hosted Kubernetes service.</p>

<p>The idea was very simple: let&rsquo;s rewrite the app
so that it batches requests to BigQuery, let&rsquo;s setup
a small k8s cluster with node autoscaling and let&rsquo;s
set the right scaling policies (<a href="https://kubernetes.io/docs/tasks/run-application/horizontal-pod-autoscale/">HPA</a>)
for our pods.</p>

<p>Rewriting the app was very easy: instead of syncing
to BigQuery at each request, we simply created a channel
that buffers up to X events, and syncs them in batch once
the buffer&rsquo;s filled up:</p>

<p>``` go
var (</p>

<pre><code>MaxWorkers     = 10
MaxQueue       = 10000
BatchSize      = 100
</code></pre>

<p>)</p>

<p>type Event struct {</p>

<pre><code>Data string
Ts   time.Time
</code></pre>

<p>}</p>

<p>func main() {</p>

<pre><code>jobs := make(chan Event, MaxQueue)
for w := 1; w &lt;= MaxWorkers; w++ {
    go worker(jobs)
}

http.HandleFunc("/track-me", func(w http.ResponseWriter, req *http.Request) {
    jobs &lt;- Event{Data: req.URL.Query(), Ts: time.Now()}
    io.WriteString(w, "ok")
})

log.Printf("Server listening on port %s", os.Getenv("PORT"))
log.Fatal(http.ListenAndServe(":"+os.Getenv("PORT"), nil))
</code></pre>

<p>}</p>

<p>func worker(events &lt;-chan Event) {</p>

<pre><code>ctx := context.Background()
client, err := bigquery.NewClient(ctx, PROJECT_ID)
if err != nil {
    panic(err) // YOLO!
}
buffer := []*Event{}

for e := range events {
    u := client.Dataset(DATASET).Table(TABLE).Uploader()
    buffer = append(buffer, &amp;e)
    if len(buffer) == BatchSize {
        log.Printf("Flushing %d events to BQ", BatchSize)
        if err := u.Put(ctx, buffer); err != nil {
            log.Printf("%s", err)
        }
        log.Printf("work done")
        buffer = []*Event{}
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>Next in line was to create the k8s cluster, which was
an extremely simple operation from GKE&rsquo;s interface:
we deployed our pods, setup an ingress and&hellip; &hellip;boom,
the app was live under a different URL!</p>

<p>Last but not least, we wanted to make sure that spikes
in traffic were taken care of, both from a memory and cpu
standpoint:</p>

<p>``` yaml
apiVersion: autoscaling/v1
kind: HorizontalPodAutoscaler
metadata:
  name: tracking-app-cpu
spec:
  scaleTargetRef:</p>

<pre><code>apiVersion: apps/v1
kind: Deployment
name: tracking-app
</code></pre>

<p>  minReplicas: 4
  maxReplicas: 100</p>

<h2>  targetCPUUtilizationPercentage: 20</h2>

<p>apiVersion: autoscaling/v2beta1
kind: HorizontalPodAutoscaler
metadata:
  name: tracking-app-memory
spec:
  scaleTargetRef:</p>

<pre><code>apiVersion: apps/v1beta1
kind: Deployment
name: tracking-app
</code></pre>

<p>  minReplicas: 4
  maxReplicas: 100
  metrics:
  &ndash; type: Resource</p>

<pre><code>resource:
  name: memory
  targetAverageUtilization: 30
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>Once the HPAs were ready, we switched our tracking URLs and&hellip;</p>

<h2>Results</h2>

<p>Where do we start? Well, since we&rsquo;re all computer geeks
at the end of the day, let&rsquo;s look at our response times,
now monitored through NewRelic:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/tracking-nr.png"></p>

<p>Our 99th percentile is at <strong>less than 0.2 milliseconds</strong>
which is definitely more like what we initially planned
&mdash; we finally nailed it!</p>

<p>As far as cost is concerned, this new cluster (which, again,
manages more than 30M events a day) costs us between
$300 to $400, a ~90% price reduction compared to the cost
of running the same application on GAE.</p>

<p>If we look at the pricing report from the GCP project in question you can clearly
see the cost reduction as soon as we deployed the
application on the GKE:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/price2-gcp.png"></p>

<p>We also take advantage of a simplified setup where
we can manage the cluster through the good old <code>kubectl</code>,
and deployments are much simpler than GAE (if you ever
used GAE you know what I&rsquo;m talking about&hellip;).</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>The goal of this post is not to say that GAE is terrible,
or that GKE is the best hosting platform out there: it merely
is a report based on our own experience building a
scalable event tracking system that we moved from one platform
to the other. GAE is surely quicker to setup and includes
additional abstractions that the GKE forces you to take care
of (load balancing and SSL, just to name a couple of them), so
we recommend to think about your use case and make a reasonated
choice.</p>

<p>We truly hope you enjoyed this post! By the way, <a href="/blog/2018/09/16/namshi-is-hiring-come-and-hack-with-us/">we&rsquo;re hiring</a>!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
