<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: job | Tech @ Namshi.com]]></title>
  <link href="http://namshi.github.io/blog/categories/job/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://namshi.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2018-01-07T11:48:42+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://namshi.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Namshi]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Get that job at Namshi]]></title>
    <link href="http://namshi.github.io/blog/2016/12/06/get-that-job-at-namshi/"/>
    <updated>2016-12-06T10:54:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://namshi.github.io/blog/2016/12/06/get-that-job-at-namshi</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Inspired by <a href="https://hautelook.github.io/jekyll/update/2015/04/01/get-that-job-at-hautelook.html">HauteLook</a> who,
in turn, were inspired by <a href="http://steve-yegge.blogspot.ae/2008/03/get-that-job-at-google.html">Steve Yegge</a>,
I decided to write a small article that briefly describes what we&rsquo;re looking for
when interviewing potential candidates.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>The process</h2>

<p>Our recruitment process tends to be quite lean (with a few exceptions :)):</p>

<ul>
<li>a first, introductory chat with me to get to know each other (<em>45m</em>)</li>
<li>a chat with someone from our HR department, so that the candidate gets a solid overview on our company, the culture, benefits and so on. This is also very helpful for people who are relocating, as it&rsquo;s the best time to ask anything about working in Dubai and so on (<em>1h</em>)</li>
<li>a more technical interview with someone from our <a href="/team">tech team</a> (usually 2 of our senior engineers) (<em>1/2h</em>)</li>
</ul>


<p>Additionally, depending on the candidate and the position, there <strong>might</strong> be a
few additional steps required:</p>

<ul>
<li>coding challenge (<em>no deadlines, should take up to 2 hours of your time</em>)</li>
<li>additional technical screening with me (<em>1h</em>)</li>
<li>chat with one of our managing directors (<em>45m</em>)</li>
</ul>


<p>So you can generally assume that, after 3 positive interviews (&frac34; hours in total), you
could theoretically receive an offer letter.</p>

<p>Expect the whole process to take around 3 weeks.</p>

<h2>Backend</h2>

<p>You should be familiar with minimalist frameworks like Express or Silex, as that&rsquo;s
how we build 99% of our services nowadays. We&rsquo;re not big on any particular language,
but if you worked with Node that&rsquo;s definitely a plus, as well as understanding
async programming.</p>

<p>Being familiar with a shell is kind of a must, as we want people who can poke
around with Linux and are aware of the potential of the &ldquo;<em>do one thing and do it well</em>&rdquo;
philosophy.</p>

<p>The HTTP protocol (both 1.1 and 2) is another must as that&rsquo;s what we speak each
and every day &mdash; you will be mainly tasked to write applications that talk to
other services through HTTP. Knowing what changes with HTTP/2 and why that&rsquo;s
great shows the kind of awareness we&rsquo;re looking for.</p>

<p>We&rsquo;re not big on algorithms and data structures but that doesn&rsquo;t mean you
shouldn&rsquo;t be able to understand them &mdash; having some basic knowledge of Big O
is always appreciated, as well as understanding how to pick a data structure in
order to make the most out of it.</p>

<p>We use both relational and non-relational databases, and you should be
comfortable with a few names here (mostly MySQL and Redis). On MySQL, questions
about race conditions, locking and <code>ALTER TABLE</code> might come up.</p>

<h2>Frontend</h2>

<p>This position is all about JS &mdash; forget CSS, forget HTML: 99% of this position
will mean JavaScript.</p>

<p>Callbacks? Promises? async / await? Breakfast for you :)</p>

<p>You should be familiar with technologies like Angular 1 and React, and how they
work behind the curtain. We could ask you to write a simpler, smaller version of
redux so you&rsquo;d better understand how these libraries work.
For example, knowing that virtual DOM makes things faster won&rsquo;t cut it &mdash; why,
how and thanks to what data structure will.</p>

<p>We also have a keen eye on performance, and you should too: understanding what
changes HTTP/2 brings to frontend engineering is a must, as well as knowing basic
rules for performance optimization (<code>webpack -p</code> anyone?). We aren&rsquo;t super-fussy
about the more advanced stuff, but if you mention tree-shaking and friends we
won&rsquo;t mind :)</p>

<p>You should be familiar with methodologies such as BEM as you will be required to
discuss what&rsquo;s the best approach to structure our styles for the long run.
We also like to sometimes use CSS animations, so knowing how to make them perform
better, especially for mobile browsers, is highly appreciated.</p>

<h2>DevOps</h2>

<p>You should be very familiar with AWS or similar providers ie. Google Cloud, and
have some sort of experience with containers and orchestrators &mdash;
we use Kubernetes but if you worked with Mesos / Swarm we won&rsquo;t really mind.
A good answer to &ldquo;<em>Why would you want to use an init system inside a container?</em>&rdquo;
will definitely speed up the hiring process :)</p>

<p>Be big on Linux, as we expect you to be a ninja there &mdash; utilities
like <code>awk</code>, <code>sed</code> and so on should be music to your ears.</p>

<p>You should be familiar with one scripting language (make it python, ruby, php, bash)
and be open to jump into code, as you might be required to provide bugfixes on
some of our services, or implement system-related features. In general, the more
you can code the happier everyone is!</p>

<p>A keen eye on security is a big plus &mdash; we&rsquo;re a small team and we need brilliant
people who are going to take into account the problems that might happen when
using (or <strong>not using</strong>) a particular technology, pattern or methodology.</p>

<p>We are also big fans of automation and, in some sense, immutable infrastructures.
Know the basics.</p>

<h2>And we also generally look for&hellip;</h2>

<ul>
<li>automated testing is king here: despite the fact that we don&rsquo;t try to cover
100% of the use-cases, we rely on automated tests a lot. Knowing how to write
them, and what methodologies to use to make tests more maintainable is a must.</li>
<li>it would be great to see some of your code &mdash; github is a fan-favorite here :)</li>
<li>people who like <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shawarma">shawarma</a></li>
</ul>


<p>What are you waiting for? Drop everything and <del>order some shawarma</del> <a href="/join-us/">apply now</a>!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Like Android and iOS? Let's change shopping in the Middle East together!]]></title>
    <link href="http://namshi.github.io/blog/2014/06/03/like-android-and-ios-lets-change-shopping-in-the-middle-east-together/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-03T16:42:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://namshi.github.io/blog/2014/06/03/like-android-and-ios-lets-change-shopping-in-the-middle-east-together</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Do you like Java? Ok, I possibly started from the wrongest question.</p>

<p>Restart.</p>

<p>Do you like Android? (sounds much better!) And what about iOS? Tablets?
Mobile devices in general? If so, come over and let&rsquo;s change the way
people shop in the Middle East.</p>

<p>We are looking for a <strong>Lead Mobile Developer</strong>, someone who can get his hands
dirty with both of the main platforms, and teach others how to do it: we&rsquo;d
like you to bring in your expertise and help kicking off our mobile
development team.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>What do we need?</h2>

<p>Our need is to kickoff an internal development team, which could even be split by
iOS and Android, and to do so we would need to make a first, very good hire and
find a lead who can drive all the way to success.</p>

<p>How will your typical day look like? You will go over a <a href="https://gist.github.com">gist</a> which has the specs for
a feature together with the other leads, wrap up a bugfix for the next release,
check one of the pull requests submitted by another team member and have
<a href="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/d/d4/Shawarma_ad_Istanbul_(01.10.2008).JPG">lotsa shawarma</a> for lunch.</p>

<p>As general rules, we would like:</p>

<ul>
<li>someone who speaks both <strong>Android and iOS</strong> (if you know only one of them but think you deserve a position, talk to us and we&rsquo;d be very happy to hear your point)</li>
<li>a few years of proficient <strong>development of mobile applications</strong>, possibly being a leader of a small/mid-sized team</li>
<li>knowledge of the <strong>latest trend</strong> in your technical sector (you tell us if <a href="http://www.omgchrome.com/android-webview-auto-update-future/">android auto-updates its webview component</a>, not the other way round :) as well as suggesting tools like <a href="http://hockeyapp.net/features/">Hockey</a>)</li>
<li><strong>Object-Oriented design</strong>: sounds boring but we don&rsquo;t limit ourselves to MVC, we actually need you to <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/odino/dont-screw-it-up-how-to-build-durable-web-apis-phpday-2014-in-verona-ita">consume our APIs and get the most out of them</a></li>
<li>it would be a plus to get someone who is passionate about <strong>OSS</strong> and would like to release some of our stuff after polishing them for the public</li>
</ul>


<h2>What do we offer?</h2>

<ul>
<li>a good salary, we don&rsquo;t want to hire people who feel they&rsquo;ve been underpaid</li>
<li>SPDY, HTTP APIs and a Service-Oriented Architecture</li>
<li>a <a href="https://www.google.com/maps/dir/First+Gulf+Bank+Metro+Station+1+-+Sheikh+Zayed+Rd+-+Dubai+-+United+Arab+Emirates/More+Cafe+Gold+%26+Diamond+Park+-+Sheikh+Zayed+Rd+-+Dubai+-+United+Arab+Emirates/@25.1264065,55.2068206,18z/data=!3m1!4b1!4m14!4m13!1m5!1m1!1s0x3e5f6bc621973f29:0x18a89384f349bdf6!2m2!1d55.207756!2d25.126699!1m5!1m1!1s0x3e5f6bc6122edfe3:0x435be27ccd3d1564!2m2!1d55.208316!2d25.126114!3e2">1-minute-walk</a> from the metro to the office</li>
<li>a <a href="/team">great team</a></li>
<li>you <strong>will and won&rsquo;t</strong> be alone: our team is made of ~15 software engineers and we share best practices at the architectual / software design level,
but don&rsquo;t have a way to re-invent the current team members into mobile hackers</li>
<li>growth, as mobile is getting bigger and bigger (for us and for the ecommerce market in general): we expect the mobile
development team to be growing as months will go by</li>
<li>a company which is standing on the <a href="http://www.rocket-internet.de/">shoulder of giants</a></li>
<li>the <em>&ldquo;10th our breakpoint&rdquo;</em>: if you work for 10 hours then have a break, order food and we will reimburse it</li>
<li>working with <a href="http://instagram.com/p/gpSOCenpPI/">these two guys</a></li>
</ul>


<h2>So what?</h2>

<p>Simply drop an email at <code>alessandro.nadalin@namshi.com</code> and let&rsquo;s make it real! Need more infos? Check <a href="/join-us">this</a>!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Looking for some fun with APIs or JavaScript? We have what you need!]]></title>
    <link href="http://namshi.github.io/blog/2014/03/24/looking-for-some-fun-with-apis-or-javascript-we-have-what-you-need/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-24T14:37:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://namshi.github.io/blog/2014/03/24/looking-for-some-fun-with-apis-or-javascript-we-have-what-you-need</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>To the army of developers out there: if you are looking to
boost your nerditude and have some fun, we might have what
you are looking for.</p>

<p><em>(no, it&rsquo;s not a cookie)</em></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Here at <a href="https://en-ae.namshi.com">Namshi</a>, in the cold (yes, it&rsquo;s an euphemism) lands of Dubai, things have gone quite well
so far, and we&rsquo;re extremely excited everytime there&rsquo;s room for
someone else in our little room (actually, our office it&rsquo;s kind of an open-space).</p>

<p>I am very happy to announce that we are now actively looking for 2
new members of our <a href="/team">team</a> in order to expand our team, vision,
objectives and count of the <a href="https://www.google.com/search?q=shisha&amp;espv=2&amp;es_sm=125&amp;source=lnms&amp;tbm=isch&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=zA8wU46_CoezhAePwgE&amp;ved=0CAkQ_AUoAQ&amp;biw=1687&amp;bih=871">shishas</a> we order when we&rsquo;re out together.</p>

<h2>API monkey</h2>

<p>If you know what the <code>PSR-4</code> is&hellip;</p>

<p>If you are willing to switch to HHVM, in production, in the next six months&hellip;</p>

<p>If you have ever heard of Event Sourcing&hellip;</p>

<p>If you get excited everytime someone names Redis (even if it&rsquo;s for no apparent reason at all, the important is to get excited regardless)&hellip;</p>

<p>If you know the 5 tenets of the REST architectural style&hellip;</p>

<p>if you want to give back to the <a href="https://github.com/namshi">opensource community</a></p>

<p>If you like <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shawarma">shawarma</a>&hellip;</p>

<p>&hellip;if all of this and that, then think of coming over to Dubai to join
a startup that has been disruptive in his market and has been writing
a Service-Oriented Architecture (with <a href="http://www.styleisnecessity.com/2012/12/15/namshi-2/">style</a>! :&ndash;))
based on Symfony2, HTTP APIs and Redis.</p>

<p>We are looking for a <em>Senior API engineer</em>, and will offer a competitive
retribution plus some other benefits (<a href="/images/cirpo.jpg">working with cirpo</a>, among others).</p>

<h2>Frontend ducktyper</h2>

<p>As a <em>Senior Frontend Engineer</em>, you will need to get bored with old school
technologies like <strong>NodeJS, AngularJS, Gulp</strong>, on which our frontends are
currently running (to be honest, if we had to rewrite today, we would go
for PERL, #FORSURE).</p>

<p>Unfortunately, your duties will also include having to deal with the DevTools
in order to speed up performances and eliminate any waste and overengineering
we might have on our frontends.</p>

<p>Last but not least &ndash; I know, I&rsquo;m sorry :( &ndash; you will be disgusted to be consuming our backend APIs,
trying to get your head around HTTP headers, caching and everything bad about webservices.</p>

<p>Ah, I almost forgot to mention that we might have to add SPDY and WebP. Yesterday.</p>

<h2>About Namshi</h2>

<p>We honestly want to keep it cool and fun, that&rsquo;s why I wante to give this
post this kind of tone.</p>

<p>One thing I am really proud of, at Namshi, is that <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/odino/soa-with-symfony2-confoo-2014-in-montreal-ca/159">we don&rsquo;t stick to one
technology</a> just because we think that we can do everything with it, we use the
correct technology for each and every context. <strong>We use what makes sense</strong>, which
means that even PERL could do something, one day, in our architecture.</p>

<p>We&rsquo;d like to hire someone who relies on the community around him, who likes
to write open source code (and use it as well!), someone who likes enterprise
design patterns and is afraid every time a feature not covered by a test goes to production.</p>

<p>The team has been steadily growing since I joined the company in 2012,
both from an headcount perspective and the level of skills.</p>

<p>Our guys and girls tend to have fun on a daily basis, commit to the company
values (and to github as well!) and (I hope :-P) are having a great run
with technologies that is not always possible to use in other scenarios.</p>

<p>But we are also aware that without other points of view, without growth,
without some fresh energy, our journey to perfection would be even harder
(and I personally make it even harder, I know!).</p>

<p>Even though we are happy with our stack and what we achieved so far, we&rsquo;re aware that
we are far from being perfect: that&rsquo;s why we need <strong>you</strong> :)</p>

<p>Drop us an email (<code>alessandro.nadalin@namshi.com</code>) and let&rsquo;s have fun together!</p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/namshi">github</a>
<a href="https://twitter.com/technamshi">twitter</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
