<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Phpunit | Tech @ Namshi.com]]></title>
  <link href="http://namshi.github.io/blog/categories/phpunit/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://namshi.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2018-09-17T11:52:50+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://namshi.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Namshi]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Frameworks And Tests in Namshi]]></title>
    <link href="http://namshi.github.io/blog/2013/09/23/frameworks/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-23T15:44:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://namshi.github.io/blog/2013/09/23/frameworks</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As Namshi developers we spend our time doing tickets and coding tasks every day to enhance the
website. However these changes are not stable all the time, sometimes some of these new changes
end up breaking other working parts of our applications without a prior alert until after we deploy it on
our website. As a result we end up having some bugs and hot fixes either immediately after testing the
new deployment or later on when people spot the bugs. Therefore Intensive QA is important because the
manual test only is not enough, even though if we were careful sometimes we’ll probably forget to test
all the affected parts by our changes. And after any deployment we need to test everything and if something
was broken we would need to fix is ASAP.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>We were working with <a href="http://framework.zend.com/">Zend Framework</a> which is considered as a good
framework for MVC projects, but we decided to move to <a href="http://symfony.com/">Symfony2</a> as it is more
user-friendly to enhance the structure of our projects and make it more organized, service based applications
and most importantly to build automated unit tests. Automated tests are mainly important for testing our tickets
and changes before/after they are deployed for quality assurance purposes. Moreover, such tests need to be
integrated at early stages because it’s very hard to add them after the development of your application.
Therefore, such tests need to be implemented in parallel with your application to make sure you cover
all units and aspects of your application.</p>

<h4>Testing our project using phpunit</h4>

<p>Quality assurance is one of the most important aspects in application development, there are several tests
that can be used for web applications like:</p>

<ul>
<li><h5>Unit Test</h5></li>
</ul>


<p>Unit Tests are usually conducted to test classes and functions within the application itself. It tests how
some functions interact with others and if the desired output and behavior are obtained.</p>

<ul>
<li><h5>Functional Test</h5></li>
</ul>


<p>Functional test is mainly used test the integration between our application [Namshi] and other services
and layers.</p>

<p>This test is useful for checking how our application functions and interacts with internal and external services.</p>

<h4>Why do we waste time on implementing automated tests</h4>

<p>If we develop our applications without writing automated tests to save time, we will end up spending more
time in fixing issues after each deployment. therefore adding automated tests will save our time,
ensure the quality of our application and help us gaining the trust of our customers.</p>

<h4>How to implement automated test</h4>

<p>With the help of symfony2 implementing automated tests is much easier and feasible. First of all you will
need to install <a href="http://phpunit.de/manual/current/en/index.html">phpunit</a> and then develop the test and
 implement it in your application.</p>

<h4>Would automated test modify the application&rsquo;s data</h4>

<p>Automated tests should not affect/modify any data in our application. Therefore we create new databases
for the testing environment, then we use data fixtures
<a href="http://symfony.com/doc/current/bundles/DoctrineFixturesBundle/index.html">DoctrineFixturesBundle</a>
to insert dummy data into the testing databases, and finally we add/delete required data before/after each test.</p>

<h4>Testing <a href="http://namshi.com/">Namshi</a></h4>

<p>We are implementing our tests for our application and all the services that interact with it.
 Our purpose is to cover all aspects of <a href="http://namshi.com/">Namshi</a> with automated test (functional test or unit test)
 to ensure the quality of our application and optimize it.</p>

<p>for now we implemented around 200 test cases
<img class="center" src="/images/posts/test-result-success.png" title="test result" ></p>

<p>These tests won&rsquo;t pass if we have any bugs of the application
<img class="center" src="/images/posts/test-result-failure.png" title="test result" ></p>

<h4>How we assert test results?</h4>

<p>we can assert test results in different ways depending on the response that we are expecting:
<code>
$this-&gt;assertEquals(400, $response-&gt;getStatusCode());
$this-&gt;assertContains("Expected text", $crawler-&gt;filter('*')-&gt;text());
</code></p>

<p>we can also use <a href="http://php.net/manual/en/class.domxpath.php">DOMXPath</a> to filter html result
<code>
$xpath  = new DOMXPath($doc);
$this-&gt;assertContains('expected value', $xpath-&gt;query("//td[@class='html tag class']")-&gt;item(0)-&gt;nodeValue);
</code></p>

<p>or we can expect exceptions
```
/<em>*
 * @expectedException \Namshi\EntityBundle\Exception\InvalidPaymentMethod
 </em>/
 public function testServiceWithInvalidPaymentMethod()
 {</p>

<pre><code>$data   = initial data
$result = $service-&gt;execute($data);
</code></pre>

<p> }
```</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
