<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: team | Tech @ Namshi.com]]></title>
  <link href="http://namshi.github.io/blog/categories/team/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://namshi.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-09-01T09:47:23+04:00</updated>
  <id>http://namshi.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Namshi]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Welcome Daniel!]]></title>
    <link href="http://namshi.github.io/blog/2014/08/31/welcome-daniel/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-31T21:37:00+04:00</updated>
    <id>http://namshi.github.io/blog/2014/08/31/welcome-daniel</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>{% img team left /images/daniel.png %}</p>

<p>We are very excited to welcome <a href="/team#Daniel%20Ribeiro">Daniel</a> in
the crazy Namshi family!</p>

<p>Daniel Ribeiro is a Technical Leader, Senior Software Engineer,
PHP 5.3 Zend Certified Engineer (ZEND021458), Speaker and
Evangelist from Brazil. He’s also a member of the local
PHP community (PHPSC), and has been working with software
engineering since 2006. His focus is on software engineering
best practices, both concerning the code and the process of
software development. He has a quite solid experience with agile
practices and leading development teams to enterprise application
standards and practices. Technically, he works with a lot of
best practices, such as Behavior-Driven Development (BDD). He
also has a background on architecture patterns, such as Domain
Driven Design (DDD) and Service Oriented Architecture (SOA). He
loves to work with high quality code, especially concerning
advanced software engineering concepts, such as the SOLID
principles and the GoF design patterns.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>I am personally very excited as Daniel and me have been
talking about working together for a while, and we finally
managed to get a chance of getting hands down to the code
together!</p>

<p>He will bring good seniority to our team as well as good
knowledge of best practices and enterprise <em>modus operandi</em>;
last but not least, Daniel has been eager to accept the challenge
of taking a closer look at NodeJS as it&rsquo;s getting bigger and
bigger in our stack.</p>

<p>Looking forward to get the brazilian vibes at our desks!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[We're hiring...actually, we're hiring MOAR!]]></title>
    <link href="http://namshi.github.io/blog/2014/08/13/were-hiring-dot-dot-dot-actually-were-hiring-moar/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-13T12:14:00+04:00</updated>
    <id>http://namshi.github.io/blog/2014/08/13/were-hiring-dot-dot-dot-actually-were-hiring-moar</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Just an heads up that we are looking for talented
engineers for our tech team, and our guys are very
sad they don&rsquo;t have too many new friends!</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Besides looking for a Lead Mobile developer, as we
<a href="/blog/2014/06/03/like-android-and-ios-lets-change-shopping-in-the-middle-east-together/">announced a few weeks back</a>,
we are looking for some other key figures in our team.</p>

<h2>No HTML/CSS love&hellip;</h2>

<p>Our frontend team, usually happy to write AngularJS
directives or a bunch of frontend-ish NodeJS apps,
is devastated as they feel they are missing a third
element who can help them achieve greatness.</p>

<p>{% img center /images/frontend-sad.png %}</p>

<p>To make Lucio and Shidhin happy, we want to add a new
member in our team, a <strong>Frontend Developer</strong>, someone who
is skilled on HTML5 and CSS3 and knows the basics of
JavaScript but wants to expand his knowledge in that
direction.</p>

<p>You will work on a whole lot of new internal applications
as well as help streamlining our frontend processes, together
with the rest of the team: which frameworks shall we use? Bootstrap or
Foundation? How can we use Yeoman&rsquo;s generator to speed up
most of our code generation? How can we make our web apps
faster <a href="https://github.com/addyosmani/critical">extracting critical styles</a>
and so on? These are just a few questions you will need to
ask yourself once you come here.</p>

<p>You will come here knowing how to design a frontend (mastering
the presentation layer, so HTML, CSS, jQuery) but will leave Namshi
knowing how to build the presentation and logic behind a full
frontend application (AngularJS, Node or something more spicy
like <a href="http://www.polymer-project.org/">polymer</a>).</p>

<blockquote><p>Drop us an email at <a href="&#109;&#97;&#105;&#x6c;&#x74;&#x6f;&#58;&#119;&#111;&#x72;&#x6b;&#x2d;&#105;&#x6e;&#x2d;&#116;&#101;&#x63;&#x68;&#x40;&#110;&#97;&#109;&#x73;&#104;&#105;&#x2e;&#x63;&#111;&#x6d;">&#119;&#x6f;&#x72;&#107;&#45;&#x69;&#x6e;&#45;&#x74;&#x65;&#x63;&#104;&#x40;&#110;&#x61;&#109;&#115;&#104;&#x69;&#x2e;&#x63;&#x6f;&#x6d;</a> to apply or simply
get more informations about this job opening!</p></blockquote>

<h2>Sitting on an empty (sysadmin) chair&hellip;</h2>

<p>Look at the systeam, so sad: they really
need some new buddy for their games.</p>

<p>{% img center /images/sys-sad.png %}</p>

<p>The chair is empty, and that makes me so sad! If only
we could find someone who would like to come and join
the hottest SOA of the Middle East&hellip;</p>

<p>So yeah, we&rsquo;re also looking for a <strong>System Administrator</strong>,
someone who knows how configuration management works,
who has relevant experience on cloud infrastructures as
AWS and wants to use some of the latest technologies, like
Docker or Deis, to help us automate and scale the hell out
of our architecture; we are trying to switch towards a more
devops oriented organization, and need someone with that
mindset to improve the current state of the team: as an example,
we use <a href="http://serverspec.org/">serverspec</a> to test some of
our configurations, and would like someone who can get his/her
hands dirty with both programming and system administration
to help the team.</p>

<blockquote><p>Drop us an email at <a href="&#109;&#x61;&#x69;&#108;&#116;&#111;&#58;&#x77;&#111;&#x72;&#x6b;&#x2d;&#x69;&#110;&#45;&#x74;&#x65;&#99;&#x68;&#x40;&#x6e;&#x61;&#109;&#x73;&#x68;&#105;&#46;&#99;&#111;&#x6d;">&#x77;&#111;&#114;&#x6b;&#45;&#x69;&#x6e;&#45;&#116;&#101;&#99;&#x68;&#x40;&#x6e;&#x61;&#x6d;&#x73;&#104;&#x69;&#46;&#x63;&#111;&#x6d;</a> to apply or simply
get more informations about this job opening!</p></blockquote>

<h2>I don&rsquo;t know if he&rsquo;s crying because of loneliness or because of NodeJS&hellip;</h2>

<p>Look at how sad Cirpo, our lead API engineer, was
today:</p>

<p>{% img center /images/cirpo-sad.png %}</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s true that he might be sad because we decided
to use a lot of NodeJS instead of PHP, but I
think his struggles also come from the fact that he feels
we need a good <strong>Senior Software engineer</strong>, specialized in
NodeJS, who can help the team getting more skilled with
this &ldquo;new&rdquo; platform.</p>

<p>The ideal candidate would have a few years of experience
on production-ready Node systems, and it would be a great
plus if we can get someone who has a broader experience
with different programming paradigms, as we feel the most
important part of this job is the brain, and it would be great
if we get someone that has been in a few different battlefields :)</p>

<p>We need someone who first solves the problem, then writes the
code (or, even better: first solves the problem, then writes the
test, then the code :-D).</p>

<blockquote><p>Drop us an email at <a href="&#109;&#x61;&#105;&#108;&#x74;&#111;&#58;&#x77;&#x6f;&#114;&#x6b;&#45;&#105;&#110;&#45;&#x74;&#x65;&#99;&#x68;&#64;&#x6e;&#97;&#109;&#115;&#x68;&#105;&#46;&#x63;&#111;&#109;">&#119;&#111;&#114;&#107;&#45;&#x69;&#110;&#x2d;&#116;&#101;&#x63;&#104;&#64;&#110;&#97;&#109;&#x73;&#x68;&#105;&#46;&#99;&#x6f;&#109;</a> to apply or simply
get more informations about this job opening!</p></blockquote>

<h2>About Namshi</h2>

<p>We have a <a href="/join-us">JOIN US</a> page where we listed some of the key
benefits in working with us, but to recap the most important ones:</p>

<ul>
<li>the environment is great, young and people are passionate</li>
<li>the office is 1 minute away from the metro station</li>
<li>we offer competitive salaries</li>
<li>flexible working hours</li>
<li>being paid to write <a href="https://github.com/namshi">Open Source code</a></li>
<li>cakes! cakes! cakes!</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Goodbye Lucianino!]]></title>
    <link href="http://namshi.github.io/blog/2014/07/02/goodbye-lucianino/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-02T22:37:00+04:00</updated>
    <id>http://namshi.github.io/blog/2014/07/02/goodbye-lucianino</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This week one of our teammates left the team
to pursuit his next big challenge: we are talking
about <a href="http://tech.namshi.com/team/#Luciano%20Amodio">Luciano</a>
who is now in Spain, hacking, as usual, with
JavaScript.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><em>Lucianino</em>, as we liked to call him, has been
instrumental in kicking off
our whole &ldquo;frontend&rdquo; department, and we have been
very happy to have him here, introducing us to
the magical world of AngularJS, Grunt (even though
we now use Gulp) and Single-Page Apps.</p>

<p>While at Namshi, we&rsquo;ve seen him transitioning
from the (traditional) world of PHP to JavaScript
and even giving his very <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/adamquadmon/angular-js-mobile-jsday-2014-verona-14-may">first talk at a conference</a>.</p>

<p>We really want to thank him for what he has done
in the past 12 months at Namshi and wish him
good luck for his next adventure!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[When you start working as a software developer...]]></title>
    <link href="http://namshi.github.io/blog/2014/06/24/when-you-start-working-as-a-software-developer-dot-dot-dot/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-24T23:30:00+04:00</updated>
    <id>http://namshi.github.io/blog/2014/06/24/when-you-start-working-as-a-software-developer-dot-dot-dot</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>&hellip;it&rsquo;s always a joy, full of surprises: what they don&rsquo;t tell you
is that not all of the surprises are much fun.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Kudos to <a href="http://tech.namshi.com/team/#Mohamad%20Hallal">Mohamad</a>
who shared his <a href="http://mohdhallal.github.io/blog/2014/06/18/my-top-10-junior-developer-pitfalls/">10 most dramatic moments as a Junior software engineer</a>
in his latest blog post: the whole team at Namshi had so much fun going through
it because:</p>

<ul>
<li>we heard him shouting at Vim</li>
<li>we&rsquo;ve all been there :)</li>
</ul>


<p>&hellip;and what about you? Which ones were your biggest #EPICFAIL?</p>

<p>On a side note, it&rsquo;s great to see how passionate engineers like
Mohamad grown on a daily basis &mdash; especially compared to the
&ldquo;old guys&rdquo; like me: one of his open source libraries,
<a href="https://github.com/namshi/mockserver">Mockserver</a>,
is definitely something you should check out.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Wanna join us? We have cookies, Symfony2, Node, AngularJS and coding challenges for you!]]></title>
    <link href="http://namshi.github.io/blog/2014/06/08/wanna-join-us-we-have-cookies-symfony2-node-angularjs-and-coding-challenges-for-you/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-08T11:44:00+04:00</updated>
    <id>http://namshi.github.io/blog/2014/06/08/wanna-join-us-we-have-cookies-symfony2-node-angularjs-and-coding-challenges-for-you</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A quick update from the trenches: for the past months
we&rsquo;ve been beefing our team up and by doing so we
realized that some good coding challenges are
almost a must.</p>

<p>We just put all the challenges we&rsquo;ve used and are gonna
be using on a <a href="https://github.com/namshi/coding-challenges">github repo for you to check them out</a>:
feel free to solve them, fork them, improve them, do anything
with them! :)</p>

<p>We are currently hiring <a href="https://github.com/namshi/coding-challenges/blob/master/senior-api-engineer.md">senior API engineers</a>, <a href="https://github.com/namshi/coding-challenges/blob/master/senior-frontend-engineer.md">senior frontend
engineers</a> and are looking to bootstrap our mobile team
with a <a href="https://github.com/namshi/coding-challenges/blob/master/lead-mobile-engineer.md">Lead Mobile Engineer</a>:
got leads? Got skills? Reach out and let&rsquo;s do Service-Oriented Architectures together!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
