<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: team | Tech @ Namshi.com]]></title>
  <link href="http://namshi.github.io/blog/categories/team/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://namshi.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2019-02-21T12:28:12+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://namshi.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Namshi]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Women in Tech @ Namshi: Ming Hu]]></title>
    <link href="http://namshi.github.io/blog/2018/12/11/women-in-tech-at-namshi-ming-hu/"/>
    <updated>2018-12-11T11:28:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://namshi.github.io/blog/2018/12/11/women-in-tech-at-namshi-ming-hu</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Here at Namshi we have quite a bit of a <a href="/team">diverse team</a> but, like many companies
out there, struggle with the gender gap in tech.</p>

<p>We, though, would like
to share the story and advices from the women who are part of our team, with the
hope that they&rsquo;ll inspire others to join us, or to simply give computer science, or
programming in general, a go.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Without further ado, let me introduce <a href="/team#Ming%20Hu">Ming</a>, who:</p>

<blockquote><p>&hellip;holds a B.S. in Computer Science from NYU Abu Dhabi. She has been passionate about building robust web and mobile applications since college. She loves writing clean and effective code and building reliable and robust system. She joined Namshi&rsquo;s back-end team in early 2018 and is excited to learn new skills and solve new challenges. Her technical skills include Python, Java, Javascript, HTML, CSS, Heroku, Node and more. In her free time, Ming can be found checking out technical blogs, reading about blockchain or baking apple pies.</p></blockquote>

<p><strong>Can you briefly tell us a bit about yourself?</strong></p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/ming.png" width="200"></p>

<p><em>After realizing that I will not make it to the Victoria Secret’s Fashion Show (I wasn’t close), I spent years studying at a college in Abu Dhabi until I discovered my interest: working on tech solutions. So it is no surprise that I joined Namshi recently as a junior software engineer, building infrastructure tools as well as customer-facing apps. I have been a perfectionist coder and I always want my work to be impeccable. Outside work, I enjoy traveling the world, playing Nintendo Switch and eating my way through the places I visit.</em></p>

<p><strong>How did you get into programming &amp; computer science?</strong></p>

<p><em>I went to a few programming workshops out of curiosity when I was in high school in China. Back then not many people were into programming, so there were usually just three or four of us sitting in the workshops. It was probably around 2012, and I remembered learning about queues, stacks, Pascal’s triangles and some idiosyncratic algorithms. Everything was just really fascinating to me. So I started writing tiny pieces of code in Pascal (yep Pascal), but the coding activity didn’t really continue.</em></p>

<p><em>Later I entered college and I wanted to be a civil engineer and build bridges for the people. Yet it turned out I absolutely hated the mundane and complicated courses. So after a week in college, I dropped all my engineering courses and went for computer science instead. I loved it so much more, and that’s how it all started.</em></p>

<p><strong>What does your typical day at work look like?</strong></p>

<p><em>My work at Namshi is very exciting every day! I go to office around 10 AM and start by prioritizing my tasks of the day on Jira or Trello board. I always talk to my teammates at the start of the day to ask for their feedback or opinions on my tasks and solutions. I like working closely with the senior members (usually with <a href="/team#Joe%20Jean">Joe</a> or Ala), and learning new knowledge and skills from them every day. I also like singling out some big chunks of time to write code without distraction by myself. When I’m not coding, I can be find reading HackerNoon, waiting for a latte in the pantry, or just checking out what the other teams are working on.</em></p>

<p><strong>What is the most challenging project you worked on? The one that made you the proudest?</strong></p>

<p><em>The most challenging project at Namshi so far is the Apple Pay Integration on web. To be honest, I didn’t expect it to take so much time and effort for this payment integration. When I started working on it, I realized that Apple has really horrible documentation and every piece of information needs some effort to gather. I’m really proud we made it to work in the end.</em></p>

<p><em>Outside Namshi, I also worked on a human digital chatbot in college. You can check out my project video <a href="https://vimeo.com/301181868">here</a>. It was published in <a href="http://aclweb.org/anthology/W18-5027">ACL</a>, presented in Abu Dhabi National Exhibition Center and selected for SIGDIAL conference in Australia. I was really proud of it.</em></p>

<p><strong>What advice would you give to a woman considering a career in the tech industry? What do you wish you had known?</strong></p>

<p><em>I love a quote by Nelson Mandela: It always seems impossible until it’s done. I think the advice from me would be to be brave, try new things and believe in the impossibilities. Coding is a very intellectual activity and I believe everyone can learn to do it, no matter male or female, old or young.</em></p>

<p><em>If I could start over, I wish I was more engaged with finding or building a developer community in the UAE. It is always fun to work with people on projects that have real-life impacts.</em></p>

<p><strong>Thanks Ming &mdash; both for sharing your experience and keeping the Namshi backends under control! :)</strong></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Currently hiring: a CyberSecurity engineer]]></title>
    <link href="http://namshi.github.io/blog/2018/07/04/currently-hiring-a-cybersecurity-engineer/"/>
    <updated>2018-07-04T06:28:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://namshi.github.io/blog/2018/07/04/currently-hiring-a-cybersecurity-engineer</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Love penetration testing, DefCon, bug bounty programs and scrapping through lines
of code to find vulnerabilities? Then we might have the right opening for you!</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Here at Namshi we&rsquo;re committed to continuously improve our security posture, by
either <a href="/blog/2018/05/16/introducing-the-namshi-bug-bounty-program/">collaborating with security researchers across the globe</a> or with in-house expertise.</p>

<p>With this in mind, we would like to hire a security researcher that can help
us from this perspective: we see security as being a topic that will only gain additional
importance as time goes by, and we&rsquo;re committed to dedicating the right amount of time,
and money, to the cause :)</p>

<p>As a <strong>Security Engineer</strong>, you&rsquo;ll be tasked with running internal assessments, ranging
from <em>pentesting</em> our cloud infrastructure to social engineering around the office,
review our security policies and define the best strategy to improve our posture.
In addition to that, you will be actively collaborating with external researchers
through our HackerOne program, which is going to be directly under your responsibility.
On top of this, as the months will go by, you will probably spend time training
both our technical and non-technical staff to raise awareness and make sure we
got the basics covered.</p>

<p>Been into it since Kali was Backtrack? Spend time going through public bounty programs
to hack your way to a reward? Want to take on the responsibility of shaping Namshi&rsquo;s
defense? Then we’re definitely a match!</p>

<h2>Apply now!</h2>

<p>What are you waiting for? Send your application to <code>work-in-tech@namshi.com</code> and
let&rsquo;s have a chat!</p>

<p>P.S. A few months back I wrote a small piece about <a href="/blog/2016/12/06/get-that-job-at-namshi/">Namshi&rsquo;s hiring process and <em>desiderata</em></a>,
give it a look!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Currently hiring: sr. backend engineers]]></title>
    <link href="http://namshi.github.io/blog/2018/07/03/currently-hiring-sr-backend-engineers/"/>
    <updated>2018-07-03T08:52:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://namshi.github.io/blog/2018/07/03/currently-hiring-sr-backend-engineers</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Love microservices, NodeJS and distributed systems? Then we might have the right
opening for you!</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Here at Namshi we&rsquo;re constantly trying to renovate our stack by using the best
from the open source ecosystem: from <a href="https://nodejs.org/en/">NodeJS</a> to <a href="https://kubernetes.io/">Kubernetes</a>, our stack bleeds with
interesting tools to work with.</p>

<p>As a Sr. Backend Engineer, you&rsquo;ll be tasked to work on a spectrum of services
ranging from our customer-facing APIs to tools that power our logistics infrastructure.
We are a very pragmatic and experienced team, so from time to time you will see
engineers busy TDDing on a feature, whereas other times we&rsquo;re <em>straight to live</em>.
We pride of being a heterogeneous team that&rsquo;s experienced to know how and when to
abstract.</p>

<p>We run a Service-Oriented architecture with 100+ microservices where JS plays a
huge part: <a href="https://stackshare.io/namshi">our stack is comprised of many different tools</a>
and we&rsquo;re always up to experimenting in light of new, harder challenges.</p>

<p>Some of the things our backend team has been working over the past few months:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="/blog/2017/05/28/rewriting-the-catalog-api/">rewriting one of our most sensitive APIs</a>, bringing the median response time down to 30ms</li>
<li>moving <a href="/blog/2017/02/06/towards-high-availability-and-beyond/">wonky pieces of our infrastructure</a> towards high-availability</li>
<li>releasing some interesting open-source <a href="https://github.com/namshi/stackdriver-pushgateway">backend bits</a></li>
</ul>


<p>Most of our backend apps are built with NodeJS, although some of the apps
still kick it in Symfony2 or pythonic boots. With a fleet of 100+ microservices, we&rsquo;re
generally very busy trying to innovate as much as possible &mdash; and refactoring when
we need to pay our technical debt back.</p>

<p>Understand the HTTP protocol? Like deploying microservices on kubernetes? Async
programming doesn&rsquo;t scare you? Then we&rsquo;re definitely a match!</p>

<h2>Apply now!</h2>

<p>What are you waiting for? Send your application to <code>work-in-tech@namshi.com</code> and
let&rsquo;s have a chat!</p>

<p>P.S. A few months back I wrote a small piece about <a href="/blog/2016/12/06/get-that-job-at-namshi/">Namshi&rsquo;s hiring process and <em>desiderata</em></a>,
give it a look!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Women in Tech @ Namshi: Noor Ali]]></title>
    <link href="http://namshi.github.io/blog/2018/03/25/women-in-tech-at-namshi-noor-ali/"/>
    <updated>2018-03-25T10:50:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://namshi.github.io/blog/2018/03/25/women-in-tech-at-namshi-noor-ali</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Here at Namshi we have quite a bit of a <a href="/team">diverse team</a> but, like many companies
out there, struggle with the gender gap in tech.</p>

<p>We, though, would like
to share the story and advices from the women who are part of our team, with the
hope that they&rsquo;ll inspire others to join us, or to simply give computer science, or
programming in general, a go.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Without further ado, let me introduce <a href="/team#noor">Noor</a>, who:</p>

<blockquote><p>&hellip;is a telecom engineer with Masters in Computer Science from Karachi, Pakistan. She started her career as an iOS developer, enhancing her skills in Android and then Mac development. She is a diversified team player, a detail oriented resource, and a quick learner. She has keen interest in application development based on smart TV, smart watch, google glass apps, and wearable gadgets. She loves to spend time learning new technologies related to big data and mobile apps development.</p></blockquote>

<p><strong>Can you briefly tell us a bit about yourself?</strong></p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/noor.jpg" width="200"></p>

<p><em>I am an ordinary omnivert person who is telecommunications engineer by education and software engineer by profession. I am often considered as a backstage performer. I love to write blogs and do voluntarily work whenever I get time.</em></p>

<p><strong>How did you get into programming &amp; computer science?</strong></p>

<p><em>My final year project in Bachelors was on MATLAB which enhanced my programming and research skills, then later got chance to work on android platform. Based on programming concepts, got job as trainee iOS developer and hence the CS journey started. Later decided to continue education in computer science and did Masters in IT with thesis on NLP.</em></p>

<p><strong>What does your typical day at work look like?</strong></p>

<p><em>Like this:</em></p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/noor_at_work.jpg"></p>

<p><em>Jokes apart, besides working on the assigned tasks in office, I try to learn at least one thing new everyday. I manage my own sheet to track my progress.</em></p>

<p><strong>What is the most challenging project you worked on? The one that made you the proudest?</strong></p>

<p><em>All projects have different challenges and I am proud of every app I&rsquo;ve worked on. The one that made me proudest was my first mac app, LightUp. Because working on mac app was different from mobile apps, there were more challenges there like changing window size, menu controls, etc.</em></p>

<p><strong>What advice would you give to a woman considering a career in the tech industry? What do you wish you had known?</strong></p>

<p><em>Try to think out of the box and work smart, not hard.</em></p>

<p><strong>Thanks Noor &mdash; both for sharing your experience and keeping the Namshi mobile apps under
control! :)</strong></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Currently hiring: a frontend engineer]]></title>
    <link href="http://namshi.github.io/blog/2018/01/07/currently-hiring-a-frontend-engineer/"/>
    <updated>2018-01-07T12:07:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://namshi.github.io/blog/2018/01/07/currently-hiring-a-frontend-engineer</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Love React, React Native, the dom and webperf? Then we might have the right
opening for you!</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>It is no news that we&rsquo;ve been banking on the JS ecosystem
for a few years: from rolling out our first angular apps in 2013 to using React
Native in our android app, we&rsquo;ve been very busy trying to push our frontends
as far as possible.</p>

<p>We run a Service-Oriented architecture where JS plays a huge part: most of our
services are either SPAs or small NodeJS-backed APIs, and <strong>JavaScript is king</strong> at
Namshi.</p>

<p>We would like to work with someone who has a very strong background in the language,
who&rsquo;s been battling on the frontend for a few years and is not afraid to dive into
Node, if required.</p>

<p>Some of the things our frontend team has been working over the past few months:</p>

<ul>
<li>integrating React Native on our <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.namshi.android">android app</a></li>
<li><a href="/blog/2017/05/02/rebuilding-our-mobile-website/">improving conversion rate on our mobile website by 20%</a></li>
<li>releasing some interesting open-sourced <a href="https://github.com/namshi/slim-slider">frontend</a> <a href="https://github.com/namshi/dollar-dom">bits</a></li>
</ul>


<p>Most of our frontend apps are built with React, although some of the older apps
still kick it in angular boots. With a fleet of 100+ microservices, we&rsquo;re
generally very busy trying to innovate as much as possible.</p>

<p>Understand the inner workings of virtual dom? Think redux is not a replacement
for components' state? Grasp how HTTP/2 helps frontend developers?
Then we&rsquo;re definitely a match!</p>

<h2>Apply now!</h2>

<p>What are you waiting for? Send your application at <code>work-in-tech@namshi.com</code> and
let&rsquo;s have a chat!</p>

<p>P.S. A few weeks back I wrote a small piece about <a href="/blog/2016/12/06/get-that-job-at-namshi/">Namshi&rsquo;s hiring process and <em>desiderata</em></a>,
give it a look!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
