<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: team | Tech @ Namshi.com]]></title>
  <link href="http://namshi.github.io/blog/categories/team/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://namshi.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2018-01-07T11:48:42+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://namshi.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Namshi]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Currently hiring: backend and mobile engineers]]></title>
    <link href="http://namshi.github.io/blog/2017/03/09/currently-hiring-backend-mobile-developers-dubai/"/>
    <updated>2017-03-09T06:49:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://namshi.github.io/blog/2017/03/09/currently-hiring-backend-mobile-developers-dubai</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We&rsquo;re currently looking for some help in a couple areas of our tech team &mdash; why
don&rsquo;t <strong>you</strong> join us?</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Mobile</h2>

<p>Getting into the specifics, we&rsquo;ve been working with an external mobile team (3rd party)
that wrote our apps from scratch, setup an efficient testing &amp; CI strategy and a
very solid deployment workflow &mdash; as a matter of fact, we&rsquo;re very proud of our
crash rate on both platforms, with android leading at 0.05%.</p>

<p>We are comfortable with the quality of our apps and the pace of development but,
in order to take them to the next level, it&rsquo;s clear to us that we need our own
team to do that: commitment, communication and going the extra-mile are definitely
different when you&rsquo;re part of the organization.</p>

<p>On the long run the team is going to be comprised of a few engineers and a lead,
so we&rsquo;d initially like to start with:</p>

<ul>
<li>1 <strong>lead mobile developer</strong>, who should ideally have good experience on both platforms</li>
<li>1 <strong>senior iOS developer</strong></li>
<li>1 <strong>senior android developer</strong></li>
</ul>


<p>The <strong>lead mobile engineer</strong> should ideally be a very hands-on, seasoned mobile
engineer with experience leading / forming a team &mdash; he will need to
help building the team, setting the right direction, overseeing development
on both platforms and coordinating with other teams (ie. backend
or product management) on feature development and aligning priorities. We expect
him to spend around 50% of his time on development (this is still a <em>hands-on</em> position),
and the other 50% on the team, teaching practices, reviewing pull requests and so on.</p>

<p>We expect from <strong>senior engineers</strong> to be able to write clean, testable code that&rsquo;s
hard to break &mdash; a few years (4+) of experience are definitely needed (say, you
should have bumped into <code>@autoreleasepool</code> before ;&ndash;)) and you
should be very familiar with different design patterns (Delegate, Facade, etc),
concepts such as mock objects and various tools to support your workflow (ie. CI
pipelines).</p>

<h2>Backend</h2>

<p>We could definitely use some help in our backend team :)</p>

<p>Even though we&rsquo;re not in a rough spot, we would like to be able to expand
our pipeline and be able to add even more seniority to the team: our usual &ldquo;backend problem&rdquo;
is that we have lots of things we&rsquo;d like to work on / experiment with but not a lot
of engineers, thus we eventually end up giving those projects up or delaying them
too much.</p>

<p>The main technologies you would be working with are:</p>

<ul>
<li>NodeJS</li>
<li>MySQL</li>
<li>Redis</li>
<li>Solr</li>
<li>Golang</li>
<li>Symfony2</li>
<li>a bit of frontend with either Angular or React</li>
</ul>


<p>all of these in the context of our microservice-based SOA: we currently employ
50+ service in production, mostly deployed in Docker containers through Google&rsquo;s
<a href="https://kubernetes.io/">Kubernetes</a>.</p>

<p>Here we would keep in consideration candidates for both a <strong>lead</strong> and a
<strong>senior</strong> position: the current team is working well and we haven&rsquo;t felt the
need to hire a lead engineer over the past few months, but we&rsquo;re open to the
idea if we find the right candidate.</p>

<p>Needless to say, both position would be <strong>quite hands-on</strong> :)</p>

<h2>Apply now!</h2>

<p>What are you waiting for? Send your application at <code>work-in-tech@namshi.com</code> and
let&rsquo;s have a chat!</p>

<p>P.S. A few weeks back I wrote a small piece about <a href="http://tech.namshi.io/blog/2016/12/06/get-that-job-at-namshi/">Namshi&rsquo;s hiring process and <em>desiderata</em></a>,
give it a look!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Welcome Gabriel!]]></title>
    <link href="http://namshi.github.io/blog/2016/10/31/welcome-gabriel/"/>
    <updated>2016-10-31T12:32:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://namshi.github.io/blog/2016/10/31/welcome-gabriel</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Fresh new vibes in the tech team as we have a new joiner who likes to hack with
JavaScript on the browser!</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><img class="left" src="/images/gabriel.jpg" width="200"></p>

<p>Gabriel is a Frontend Engineer, who holds a B.Sc in Engineering from University
of Ibadan Nigeria.</p>

<p>He loves to build products that are functional, beautiful and easy to use.
His main focus is Frontend development (a lot of Javascript, HTML, CSS, Sass…)
and some UX to go with it (on the server NodeJS and basic PHP).</p>

<p>He loves challenging myself to do more and push beyond the limits.
His best quote is “<em>if you do it right, it would last forever – Massimo Vignelli</em>”</p>

<p>Welcome amongst the Namshees!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Currently hiring: a DevOps engineer and a JS hacker here in Dubai]]></title>
    <link href="http://namshi.github.io/blog/2016/08/07/currently-hiring-a-devops-engineer-and-a-js-hacker-here-in-dubai/"/>
    <updated>2016-08-07T11:29:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://namshi.github.io/blog/2016/08/07/currently-hiring-a-devops-engineer-and-a-js-hacker-here-in-dubai</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Hey folks, here at <a href="https://www.namshi.com">Namshi</a> we&rsquo;re currently looking
to beef our team up &mdash; without further ado, let me quickly go through both
of them!</p>

<!-- more -->


<ul>
<li><p><strong>Sr. DevOps engineer</strong>: we run our entire stack on AWS, and 99% of our
services run in Docker containers orchestrated via <a href="http://kubernetes.io/">Kubernetes</a>:
a big chunk of our infrastructure is provisioned through <a href="https://saltstack.com/">SaltStack</a>
and we like to keep things simple, reliable and robust &mdash; inspired by
<a href="https://www.infoq.com/news/2013/05/dystopia-as-a-service">Netflix&rsquo;s dystopian architecture</a>.
We believe in fault-tolerant, reactive architectures that don&rsquo;t care about a
server going down, as others will be able to take on the load, or automated checks
will make sure new HW comes online &mdash; and that&rsquo;s how we setup our live infrastructure,
where a sizable chunk of our services runs through spot instances, with confidence :)
We are now looking for someone who can help us lifting the team a step further, playing
with tools like:</p>

<ul>
<li>golang / python / bash</li>
<li>Docker</li>
<li>Kubernets / Swarm / Mesos</li>
<li>AWS</li>
<li>SaltStack / Ansible / Chef</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<p>In the past 18 months we&rsquo;ve worked on a few interesting challenges such as:</p>

<ul>
<li>implementing ChatOps</li>
<li>utilizing containers on our live infrastructure</li>
<li>integrating Terraform to automate tasks / provisioning</li>
<li>reduced our AWS bill, while growing as a company, by writing more efficient
applications and introducing spot instances in our fleet</li>
</ul>


<p>This gives you an overview of the kind of stuff we would love you to work on:
we think of DevOps engineers as a mix between software developers
and system administrators, so we&rsquo;d like you to know a bit of both :)</p>

<ul>
<li><p><strong>(Sr.) JS engineer</strong>: it is no news that we&rsquo;ve been exploring the JS ecosystem
for a few years now: from rolling out our first angular apps in 2013 to testing
React Native in the past months, we&rsquo;ve been very busy trying to push our frontends
as far as possible.
We run a Service-Oriented architecture where JS plays a huge part: most of our
services are either SPAs or small NodeJS-backed APIs, and JavaScript is king at
Namshi.
We would like to work with someone who has a very strong background in the language,
who&rsquo;s been battling on the frontend for a few years and is not afraid to dive into
Node, if required.
Some of the things our frontend team has been working over the past few weeks:</p>

<ul>
<li>React Native</li>
<li>Redux</li>
<li>MobX</li>
<li>isomorphic JavaScript</li>
<li>AMP</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<p>Most of our frontend apps are built with Angular, although we&rsquo;re heavily experimenting
with React, even for our internal tools. With a fleet of 50+ microservices, we&rsquo;re
generally very busy trying to innovate as much as possible.</p>

<p>We&rsquo;re open to very promising, junior candidates even though we&rsquo;re currently hoping
to find someone with a few years of experience on his / her back &mdash; if you feel you
do not have the experience but have the right attitude, then let&rsquo;s definitely have
a chat.</p>

<p>What are you waiting for? Drop a line at <code>work-in-tech@namshi.com</code> and let&rsquo;s
start this journey together!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Welcome Joe!]]></title>
    <link href="http://namshi.github.io/blog/2016/07/10/welcome-joe/"/>
    <updated>2016-07-10T16:36:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://namshi.github.io/blog/2016/07/10/welcome-joe</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Fresh new vibes in the tech team as
Joe joined us a today!</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><img class="right" src="/images/joe.png"></p>

<p>Joe, from Haiti, holds a B.S. in Computer Science from NYU Abu Dhabi.
He loves building software that make people&rsquo;s lives easier, and is always looking
for opportunities to improve his programming skills, whether it is by participating at a
hackathon, working on a side project, or doing technical internships.</p>

<p>His technical skills include Python, JavaScript, C, Flask, Django, HTML, CSS,
Heroku, AWS and more &mdash; however, he is language agnostic, so he likes to use the
right tool for the given task.</p>

<p>When he is not solving technical problems, you can find him reading a personal
development book or riding a bike.</p>

<p>Welcome amongst the Namshees!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ciao! So long and thanks for all the shawarma]]></title>
    <link href="http://namshi.github.io/blog/2016/02/29/ciao-thanks-for-all-the-shawarma/"/>
    <updated>2016-02-29T14:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://namshi.github.io/blog/2016/02/29/ciao-thanks-for-all-the-shawarma</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/cirpo-farewell.jpg"></p>

<p>Today is my last day at Namshi.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>I joined Namshi two and half years ago and it has been a terrific journey. At that time I was looking for an opportunity where I could work and focus on a product, on something that could have potential to become something big and relevant for the market. I bet on Namshi. And I was right.</p>

<p>It has been a terrific journey where I learned a lot and worked with amazing colleagues.
I still have a vivid memory of my first live deployment, just 3 hours after I joined the backend team: a reassurance that I was in the right place, it felt sooo good !
It’s not so common to find a place where you can contribute and <a href="http://github.com/namshi">give back to opensource</a>, experiment with new technologies or move fast and focus on things that will have real and effective impact on the business, strive for simplicity, no frills and being mentored by phenomenal people.</p>

<p>A big thank you to the Tech team, it was a real pleasure, <strong>you will be missed a lot!</strong></p>

<p>شكراً</p>

<p>آپ کا شکریہ</p>

<p>धन्यवाद</p>

<p>E se</p>

<p>Спасибо</p>

<p>Obrigado</p>

<p>Danke</p>

<p>Teşekkürler</p>

<p>Grazie</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
