<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Virus | Namshi]]></title>
  <link href="http://tech.namshi.com/blog/categories/virus/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://tech.namshi.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-02-13T19:24:23+04:00</updated>
  <id>http://tech.namshi.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Namshi]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Virus Detection and Prevention Tips]]></title>
    <link href="http://tech.namshi.com/blog/2013/12/10/virus-detection-and-prevention-tips/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-10T13:32:00+04:00</updated>
    <id>http://tech.namshi.com/blog/2013/12/10/virus-detection-and-prevention-tips</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<ul>
<li>Make sure you have an anti-virus program installed on your computer. If an anti-virus is installed, also sure its updated regularly as well.</li>
<li>Don&rsquo;t open email attachments from an unknown, suspicious or untrustworthy source. Also, be careful of email attachments you are not expecting, it might be that the sender&rsquo;s email has been compromised.</li>
<li>Delete junk emails except you are sure they not junks. Don&rsquo;t forward or reply to any to them. These types of email are
considered Spam because the authenticity of the email is not guaranteed.</li>
</ul>


<!-- more -->


<ul>
<li>Be careful when downloading files from the Internet. Be sure that the source is a legitimate and a reputable one.</li>
<li>Please stay away from torrent sites. Some of the popular ones include Limewire, BitTorrent, Frostwire and Pirate Bay are heavily laden with viruses, malware and spyware. Downloading from these websites is one of the easiest ways to become infected. It’s in your best interest to avoid these websites completely.</li>
<li>Be careful when searching on the Internet, the links that come up from your search engine may contain a virus. Never go to sites that seem suspicious.</li>
<li>Due to the popularity of the social networking websites such as MySpace, Facebook, and Twitter, virus makers target them more than any other website. Unknown Ads especially the ones that advertise free stuffs are considered high risk. Avoid clicking these links.</li>
<li>If you happen to see a pop-up message that you have been infected and to buy their software to protect yourself, do not fall for it! If you click on any part of those messages, a program will be installed which could be a virus. Immediately close the browser and don&rsquo;t open the browser page when opening the browser again.</li>
<li>If you happen see any suspicious pop-ups appear on your screen, don&rsquo;t click them. If you do, it is very likely you will infect your computer. Immediately close the browser and don&rsquo;t open the browser page when opening the browser again.</li>
<li>If you are in doubt about any potential virus related situation you find yourself in, please do not hesitate to the <a href="mailto:it@namshi.com">IT team</a> and we will answer any question you may have.</li>
</ul>


<h2>References:</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://windows.microsoft.com/en-us/windows7/tips-for-protecting-your-computer-from-viruses">http://windows.microsoft.com/en-us/windows7/tips-for-protecting-your-computer-from-viruses</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.csrinc.net/virusprevention/VirusDetectionandPreventionTips.pdf">http://www.csrinc.net/virusprevention/VirusDetectionandPreventionTips.pdf</a></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
