<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: welcome | Tech @ Namshi.com]]></title>
  <link href="http://tech.namshi.com/blog/categories/welcome/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://tech.namshi.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-07-03T12:19:00+04:00</updated>
  <id>http://tech.namshi.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Namshi]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Welcome Nikita!]]></title>
    <link href="http://tech.namshi.com/blog/2014/05/26/welcome-nikita/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-26T23:40:00+04:00</updated>
    <id>http://tech.namshi.com/blog/2014/05/26/welcome-nikita</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="team left" src="/images/nikita.png"></p>

<p>Yesterday we got some cold breeze from Russia, which
is never bad considered that Dubai is getting ready
for the summer!</p>

<p>Nikita, one of our new API engineers, has joined the
team to feed our architecture with energy, good software engineering
and a ton of rock-solid PHP development!</p>

<p>You can get to know Nikita by checking out his <a href="https://github.com/nikita2206">github profile</a>,
a place where he likes to fork the official PHP repository
to fix bugs on the language itself (kudos!) or&hellip;by starting
to check our <a href="https://github.com/namshi">github page</a> out more often,
as we&rsquo;re gonna see some more open-source PHP libraries over there!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Welcome Shidhin!]]></title>
    <link href="http://tech.namshi.com/blog/2014/05/26/welcome-shidhin/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-26T15:36:00+04:00</updated>
    <id>http://tech.namshi.com/blog/2014/05/26/welcome-shidhin</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="team left" src="/images/shidhin.jpg"></p>

<p>Second announcement of the day (and we ain&rsquo;t done yet!):
I am super-duper-excited to welcome <a href="https://twitter.com/shidhincr">Shidhin CR</a>
in the family!</p>

<p>Shidhin has been working at FlipKart for a while and,
as soon as we got to know each other, found an immediate
connection: cutting edge technologies meet a cutting-edge, motivated
brain. He will be part of our <em>Frontend Engineering</em> team,
helping on AngularJS, some of the frontend design and
JavaScript in general (Did I mention <a href="/blog/2014/03/24/looking-for-some-fun-with-apis-or-javascript-we-have-what-you-need/">we love JavaScript?</a>).</p>

<p>As he describes himself:</p>

<p><em>I am is a senior Front end developer, passionate about latest UI best practices and front end technologies. I have over 6 years of experience in front end development, and core JavaScript expertise. In the free time, I can be found updating my blog or checking out some open source stuff.</em></p>

<p>You can read more about Shidhin in his <a href="http://www.undefinednull.com/">personal blog</a>
or&hellip;starting to check our <a href="https://github.com/namshi">github page</a> out more often,
as we&rsquo;re gonna see some more AngularJS-ish stuff over there!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Welcome Lucio!]]></title>
    <link href="http://tech.namshi.com/blog/2014/05/26/welcome-lucio/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-26T11:20:00+04:00</updated>
    <id>http://tech.namshi.com/blog/2014/05/26/welcome-lucio</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="team left" src="/images/lucio.jpg"></p>

<p>I am very happy to announce &ndash; even though I&rsquo;m a bit late &ndash; that
<a href="https://twitter.com/unlucio">Luciano &ldquo;unlucio&rdquo; Colosio</a>
is part of our crazy team!</p>

<p>He&rsquo;s been quite proficient in spreading JavaScript
all around his software architectures, thus we felt he
was a perfect match for Namshi: among his past creations
there&rsquo;s even a <a href="https://github.com/unlucio/MarcoPolo">REST driver for OrientDB</a> in NodeJS.</p>

<p>Lucio will boost our frontend productivity bringing in
the software design skills we always like to welcome:
simplicity, clean code and good engineering.</p>

<p>(<em>&hellip;and they say he&rsquo;s a great chef!</em>)</p>

<p>You can read more about Lucio in his <a href="http://blog.unlucio.com/">personal blog</a>
or&hellip;starting to check our <a href="https://github.com/namshi">github page</a> out more often,
as I sense we&rsquo;re gonna see some more NodeJS there!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
