<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: node | Tech @ Namshi.com]]></title>
  <link href="http://namshi.github.io/blog/categories/node/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://namshi.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-09-01T09:47:23+04:00</updated>
  <id>http://namshi.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Namshi]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Newsletter #53]]></title>
    <link href="http://namshi.github.io/blog/2014/08/28/newsletter-number-53/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-28T16:11:00+04:00</updated>
    <id>http://namshi.github.io/blog/2014/08/28/newsletter-number-53</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p><strong>BOOM!</strong> As mentioned in the last newsletter, we were working on four new open souce libraries and two of them are already out !!!</p>

<ul>
<li><p><a href="https://github.com/namshi/shisha"><strong>shisha, smoke tests made easy!</strong></a> A cool nodejs library by <a href="http://tech.namshi.com/team/#Shidhin%20CR">Shidhin</a> and <a href="http://tech.namshi.com/team/#Mohamad%20Hallal">Hallal</a> that let&rsquo;s you
write smoke tests in an easy way.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://github.com/namshi/node-dock"><strong>node-dock, a sweet remedy for all your docker problems!</strong></a> Another node library by <a href="http://tech.namshi.com/team/#Hossam%20Faris">Hossam</a> and <a href="http://tech.namshi.com/team/##Luciano%20Colosio">Lucio</a> that
has an handy command (dock) that plugs on top of your usual docker commands adding some sugar and some handy functionality on top of it.</p></li>
<li><p>Even <a href="http://tech.namshi.com/team/#Alessandro%20Nadalin">Alex</a> released another tiny and cool node lib called <a href="http://tech.namshi.com/blog/2014/08/22/node-file-ensure-a-small-filesystem-utility-to-make-sure-a-file-is-there/"><strong>node-file-ensure</strong>, a small filesystem utility to make sure a file is there</a></p></li>
<li><p>Lucio also wrote a post detailing his first months here at Namshi: <a href="http://tech.namshi.com/blog/2014/08/27/so-far-dot-dot-dot-so-fun/">check it out</a>!</p></li>
<li><p>Last but not least, <a href="http://tech.namshi.com/team/#Geshan%20Manandhar">Geshan</a> on his vacation back home, has improvised this talk at PHP Developers Meetup Nepal on message queues (AMQP) with RabbitMQ and Symfony <a href="http://mq-talk.herokuapp.com/">http://mq-talk.herokuapp.com/</a></p></li>
</ul>
</blockquote>

<p>And here we are as usual with a list of interesting links to keep you busy during the upcoming weekend:</p>

<ul>
<li><p><a href="https://github.com/OptimalBits/redbird">A modern reverse proxy for node</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://buff.ly/1nEYH2M">Open Source ain’t Charity</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://speakerdeck.com/patrickhamann/ship-it-re-develop-conference-august-2014">Ship it! A story of continuous delivery at theguardian.com</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://www.gov.uk/service-manual/agile/running-retrospectives.html">Reviewing a team&rsquo;s work and the way it is done at Gov.uk Design Services</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://buff.ly/1wDTrGe">Plain Old #JavaScript Object Visualization</a></p></li>
</ul>


<!-- more -->


<ul>
<li><p><a href="http://t.co/eDh0CeQYpA">Stop whatever you are doing and look at p6 of this paper</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://buff.ly/1lrfCus">Rocket Internet co-founder sees venture take off in Middle East</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://buff.ly/1q9KvDq">V8&rsquo;s memory mysteries</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://buff.ly/1sh7Lhn">49ers’ stadium Wi-Fi served 25,000 concurrent users, 2.13TB in all</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://buff.ly/1mA3a6D">Software Developers and Asperger&rsquo;s Syndrome</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://buff.ly/1v8pUmg">Docker Service Discovery Using Etcd and Haproxy</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://buff.ly/1tqNB7a">Stellar: Fast database snapshot and restore tool for development</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://buff.ly/1seRoll">Javascript optimization killers</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://buff.ly/1mz2vlT">How I Hacked My Husband&rsquo;s Programming Addiction</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://mq-talk.herokuapp.com/#/14">programmming mantras to remember</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://buff.ly/1myYCxx">Facebook Unveils Its Load-Balancing System: Autoscale</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://buff.ly/1wiCeln">Docker 1.2.0, with restart policies</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://buff.ly/1lmw8vT">Semantic Versioning Is Not the Solution</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://buff.ly/1mtjtSS">The Plague of Methods and Frameworks</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://buff.ly/1s2pxot">Evolution of Docker and Its Impact on AWS &ndash; i build the cloud</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://buff.ly/1s2p4Cu">Uber opens up its API – and creates a new platform</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://www.glasswire.com">GlassWire Network Security Monitor &amp; Firewall Tool</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://netguru.co/blog/posts/procrastination-and-overcoming-programmers-block">Procrastination and Overcoming Programmer&rsquo;s Block</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://algorithm.dk/posts/rtfm-0day-in-ios-apps-g-gmail-fb-messenger-etc">RTFM 0day in iOS apps: G+, Gmail, FB Messenger</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://www.codefights.com">CodeFights &ndash; Become a Code Champion</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://hoa-project.net/En/">Hoa project, a cool set of PHP lib (they deserve more community involvement &ndash; i.e. tests are missing, own standards)</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://code.tutsplus.com/tutorials/bubblejs-a-16k-solution-to-a-common-problem--cms-21986">Bubble.js: A 1.6K Solution to a Common Problem</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://knplabs.com/blog/2011/05/17/agile-nodejs/">We love Symfony2… but we also love Agility and Node.js</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://www.codeproject.com/Articles/604417/Agile-software-development-methodologies-and-how-t">Agile software development methodologies and how to apply them</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://lafikl.github.io/perfBar/">website performance metrics</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://github.com/OptimalBits/redbird">A modern reverse proxy for node</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://mobileangularui.com/">Mobile Angular UI</a></p></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[MockServer, Effortless API Mocking Library in Node Js]]></title>
    <link href="http://namshi.github.io/blog/2014/06/13/mockserver-effortless-api-mocking-library-in-node-js/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-13T04:22:00+04:00</updated>
    <id>http://namshi.github.io/blog/2014/06/13/mockserver-effortless-api-mocking-library-in-node-js</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Namshi Tech Team is happy to roll-out a new node-based library!</p>

<p>We present you <a href="https://github.com/namshi/mockserver">MockServer</a>, a library that allows you to easily mock your APIs' plain HTTP responses.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>The main benefit of this library is to allow developers to focus on what is important to them, and in this case,
<code>mockserver</code> allows front-end developers to focus their efforts on creating awesome front-end clients without having to worry about the
availability of a complete and running API.</p>

<p>The use of this library can be appreciated by developers following a <a href="http://www.frontendfirst.com/">Front-End First</a>
methodology where development efforts initially focus on front-end clients rather than the back-end structure and tools.
Front-end first suggests that front-end developers have their mocked servers return expected or anticipated HTTP responses
based on the available specification instead of making an actual call to the API.
Another benefit is to allow development for both front-end and back-end in parallel.</p>

<p>In short, this library basically removes the dependency that the front-end development requires from the backend.</p>

<h2>Usage</h2>

<p>Create an empty directory inside your project, <code>mkdir api</code></p>

<p>To start mocking your HTTP responses, you will need to have a sub-directory were all your mocks shall reside. In order to do so,
in your <code>api</code> folder run <code>mkdir mocks</code> and that&rsquo;s where all plain text HTTP responses will reside.</p>

<p>Inside your <code>api</code> directory, run</p>

<p><code>
npm install mockserver
</code></p>

<p>Create a new js file, say, <code>api.js</code> that has the following:</p>

<p>```javascript
var http       = require(&lsquo;http&rsquo;),</p>

<pre><code>mockserver = require('mockserver');
</code></pre>

<p>http.createServer(mockserver(&lsquo;./mocks&rsquo;)).listen(&lsquo;9001&rsquo;);
```</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s it! Now navigate from your terminal to the <code>api</code> directory and run <code>node api.js</code>. This will create a node server that
listens to port <code>9001</code>.</p>

<p>Now, you should point your front-end client to <code>http://localhost:9001</code> instead of the actual api url.</p>

<h2>Mocks</h2>

<p>Now, your node server is running and your client can start making requests and getting back mocked HTTP responses.</p>

<p>How do you create the mocks?</p>

<p>Each request relative url path, HTTP method combination resides in a separate text file inside your mocks folder.
The naming of those files goes as follows: <code>path_METHOD</code>, <code>path</code> is the relative url path without any slashes, i.e, <code>/test</code>
should be <code>test</code> and <code>METHOD</code> is the upper-cased HTTP method (<code>GET</code>). The extension for the files should be <code>.mock</code>.
The complete file name is: <code>test_GET.mock</code>.</p>

<p>The contents of the mocked file should be a valid HTTP response text, as follows:</p>

<p>```
HTTP/1.1 200 OK
Content-Type: text/html; charset=utf-8</p>

<p><html><body>Hello World</body></html>
```</p>

<p>Now, whenever your client requests <code>http://localhost:9001/test</code>, <code>mockserver</code> will return that plain HTTP response you defined
in <code>test_GET.mock</code>.</p>

<h2>Header Variation</h2>

<p>Mockserver also supports different responses for the the same request path, method pair. You can make use of this feature by manually setting a
<code>mockserver-variation</code> header in your requests. The value of this header shall be appended to the mocked file name as follows: <code>path_METHOD_variation</code>.</p>

<p>Here is where you are able to handle various server HTTP responses for your request (200, 400, 500, 403, etc..).
Simply set <code>mockserver-variation</code> to <code>500</code> and the file from our previous example should be named <code>test_GET_500.mock</code>.</p>

<h2>Multi-level URLs</h2>

<p>If you are wondering how to mock HTTP responses for a multi-level URL like <code>http://localhost:9001/test1/test2</code> here is how to do it:</p>

<ul>
<li>Inside your <code>mocks</code> directory, run <code>mkdir test1</code></li>
<li><code>cd test1</code> and <code>touch test2.mock</code></li>
<li>Insert your raw HTTP response text in <code>test2.mock</code></li>
</ul>


<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>Although simple and straight forward, the idea behind <code>mockserver</code> is quite powerful. It is mostly suited for a Front-end First methodology, some of the
benefits include parallel front-end and back-end development and the decoupling of the Front-end and back-end during the development phase.</p>

<p>It would be great if you can take the time to try it out and let us know what you think!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
