<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: conference | Tech @ Namshi.com]]></title>
  <link href="http://namshi.github.io/blog/categories/conference/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://namshi.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2018-09-19T11:42:06+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://namshi.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Namshi]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[SymfonyCon Madrid 2014, the Sf2 community it's getting as stable as it can get]]></title>
    <link href="http://namshi.github.io/blog/2014/11/29/symfonycon-madrid-2014-the-sf2-community-its-getting-as-stable-as-it-can-get/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-29T17:32:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://namshi.github.io/blog/2014/11/29/symfonycon-madrid-2014-the-sf2-community-its-getting-as-stable-as-it-can-get</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Since I had the privilege of attending
the SymfonyCon in Madrid, in the past couple
of days, I thought it would be nice
to wrap up my thoughts on the event and
the state, from my point of view, of the
symfony community.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Broader expansion</h2>

<p>From what I could see, it looks like symfony
is trying to expand in a way so that it can
reach out to a <strong>bigger part of the PHP community</strong>:
both <a href="http://fabien.potencier.org/">Fabien</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/weaverryan">Ryan</a> spent a few words on how
we should make the process of embracing symfony
a bit easier and the importance of the <a href="http://symfony.com/blog/making-the-symfony-experience-exceptional">DX initiative</a>
in this direction.</p>

<p>To me, this looks like a very good move as it will
influence the community, as a whole, in a drastic way:
if we can get PHP developers to embrace, by default,
all the best practices that symfony endorses (decoupling,
testing, etc.) then we&rsquo;ve got a great road ahead of us.</p>

<p>When I first bumped into PHP I must admit that the
panorama was much messier, whereas today developers
are already used to tools like Composer, standards like
the ones promoted by the php-fig, which shows that we&rsquo;ve
improved <strong>a lot</strong>, but there&rsquo;s still a lot to do (and more
legacy to fight :)).</p>

<p>Fabien also pointed out how we shouldn&rsquo;t expect drastic changes
for Symfony 3 and the <em>leit motif</em> of his first keynote was
a focus on making the ecosystem around the framework more
complete, stable, rather than pushing towards innovation:
as you probably already know, Symfony2 is <a href="http://symfony.com/doc/current/contributing/code/bc.html">really stable</a>
and the overall feeling I had is that we won&rsquo;t see anything
technically crazy in the next couple of years but rather
see the framework and the surroundings getting simpler
and more &ldquo;complete&rdquo;.</p>

<h2>Blackfire.io</h2>

<p>I particularly appreciated one of the final presentations,
about Sensio&rsquo;s newborn <a href="https://blackfire.io/">Blackfire</a>, which looks like
a very promising tool in order to monitor performances and
optimize without too much hassle.</p>

<p>It is now in public beta so I invite you to try it on
any random project you are developing, as the <a href="https://blackfire.io/getting-started">setup</a>
literally takes 5 minutes.</p>

<h2>Time to look beyond Symfony2</h2>

<p>I should also be a little critical :)</p>

<p>One of the things that I missed, not being in the trenches
with symfony on a daily basis, were those in-depth contents
&ndash; not necessarily related to Symfony &ndash; that you will bring home
&ndash; after the conference.</p>

<p>I am talking about new technologies that can be integrated with
the framework (I tried by giving an overview about <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/odino/hey-i-just-met-angularjs-and-this-is-crazy-so-heres-my-javascript-lets-use-it-maybe">our experience with AngularJS</a>),
generic best practices (ie. <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/odino/dont-screw-it-up-how-to-build-durable-web-apis-phpday-2014-in-verona-ita">API design</a>) and so on. I actually
left the SymfonyCon without too much (technical)
inspiration.</p>

<p>(but again, this is the <strong>Symfony</strong>Con, so maybe&hellip; :))</p>

<h2>Organization</h2>

<p>Well, probably the best part of the conference: I already mentioned
<a href="http://odino.org/angularjs-almost-a-year-later/">elsewhere</a> that food and WiFi were amazing, plus Sensio did
a great job in making the speakers feel welcome.</p>

<p>It doesn&rsquo;t always happen, but when an event is <strong>facilitated
by the venue / organization / detail-orientation of the organizer</strong>
you can then spend your time focusing on what really matters
(the content) rather than complaining that the WiFi is slow,
feel hungry or tired because the venue is 2000 miles away
from the nearest, affordable hotel.</p>

<h2>What&rsquo;s next?</h2>

<p>Well, Symfony turns ten next year&hellip;and will celebrate its most
important birthday back in Paris so&hellip;hope to see you there!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Newsletter #64]]></title>
    <link href="http://namshi.github.io/blog/2014/11/06/newsletter-number-64/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-06T13:31:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://namshi.github.io/blog/2014/11/06/newsletter-number-64</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Hello friends from the software engineering community!</p>

<blockquote><p>News from the tech team:</p>

<p><a href="http://tech.namshi.io/team/#Alessandro_Cinelli">Cirpo</a>, <a href="http://tech.namshi.io/team/#Alessandro%20Nadalin">Alex</a>, <a href="http://tech.namshi.io/team/#Oluwaseun%20Obajobi">Oba</a> and Manuel went to the first Rocket Internet Global Tech Summit in Berlin last week.
Oba and Alex gave two talks about our internal technology and stack. It was a great opportunity to meet and discuss
with other tech leads from all the Rocket Internet ventures from all around the world.</p></blockquote>

<p><img class="team right" src="/images/berlin.png"></p>

<p>It&rsquo;s <a href="/blog/categories/techthursday/">#TechThursday</a> at <a href="http://twitter.com/techNamshi">#namshi</a>!</p>

<p><strong>Here is the list with awesome links to keep you busy during the weekend:</strong></p>

<ul>
<li><p><a href="https://tacoapp.com/">Taco App &ndash; a unified task list, getting tasks from 40+ sources</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://bit.ly/1BdO42A">Become a Better Programmer: 5 Essential Methods at a Glance</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://bit.ly/1qEThXn">FrontEnd Vs Backend Developer Infographic</a></p></li>
</ul>


<!-- more -->


<ul>
<li><p><a href="http://stackshare.io/">StackShare.io &ndash; Discover &amp; discuss software stacks</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://bit.ly/111sQEA">Technical Debt Takes Many Forms</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://buff.ly/1wUf5nO">Master Developers: Addy Osmani</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://buff.ly/1wnN5ow">Windows port of Docker Client by ahmetalpbalkan..things start moving!</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://buff.ly/1v4oVER">A Quick Introduction to CoreOS</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://buff.ly/1GNLOPV">Front-end Tooling Workflows // this is a GREAT presentation</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://buff.ly/1Es3nBj">Symfony 3.0: The roadmap</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://buff.ly/1v25Gf7">Amazon Deploys to Production Every 11.6 Seconds // I think now its around every 6s&hellip;</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://buff.ly/1Eq1FAf">React’s diff algorithm</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://buff.ly/1Ey5GVc">VisualOps: no more heavy lifting in the cloud</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://www.saltstack.com/salt-blog/saltstack-aws-reinvent-pagerduty">SaltStack Delivers More Advanced Cloud Orchestration for Amazon Web Services and Pagerduty</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://aws.amazon.com/codedeploy/">AWS CodeDeploy</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://aws.amazon.com/rds/aurora/">Amazon RDS for Aurora</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://devops.com/blogs/devops-scorecard/">The DevOps Scorecard</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://blog.socialcast.com/realtime-search-solr-vs-elasticsearch">Realtime Search: Solr vs Elasticsearch</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://blog.trifork.com/2013/10/24/how-to-avoid-the-split-brain-problem-in-elasticsearch/comment-page-1/">How to avoid the split-brain problem in elasticsearch</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://www.slideshare.net/kucrafal/scaling-massive-elastic-search-clusters-rafa-ku-sematext">Scaling Massive Elastic-Search Clusters</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://hhvm.h4cc.de">HHVM packages support</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://hacksummit.org/">HackSummit, a virtual conference for developers</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://keithclark.co.uk/labs/css-fps/desktop/">A 3D environment with lighting, shadows built with CSS transforms</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://futurice.com/blog/reactive-mvc-and-the-virtual-dom">Reactive mvc and the virtual dom</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://speakerdeck.com/jmikola/async-php-with-react"> Async PHP with React</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/0B3UKOMH_4lgBUTdjUGxIZ3l1Ukk/view"> A presentation about PHP 7</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://speakerdeck.com/ezimuel/information-security-in-php-the-cia-triad-approach">Information Security in PHP: the CIA Triad Approach</a></p></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Namshi went to Germany!<br>WebTechCon and International PHPConference 2014]]></title>
    <link href="http://namshi.github.io/blog/2014/10/30/ipc14-wtc14-munich/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-30T06:51:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://namshi.github.io/blog/2014/10/30/ipc14-wtc14-munich</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="/images/posts/webtech14-ipc14.png" width="320" height="320" title="&lsquo;WebTechCon&rsquo; &lsquo;WebTechCon&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>I had the opportunity to attend the <a href="http://webtechcon.de/2014/">WebTechCon</a> and the <a href="https://phpconference.com/2014">International PHPConference 2014</a> as speaker in Munich, Germany.
The location was very nice, and beeing a foodie, the food was great :).</p>

<p>The only small complaint I have is that in 2014, Tech conference should be in English: I missed a lot of potentially great talks because they were in German.</p>

<p>The International PHP Conference is the world&rsquo;s first PHP conference and stands since more than a decade while the WebTechCon is taking place
since the last 5 years.
The fact that you have these two events combined confirms the trend of horizontal events rather than focusing on just
one technology or product.
Lots of different topics were covered: PHP, Javascript, HTML5, AngularJs, databases, devops, systems, automation, architecture etc.</p>

<p>The concept of an heterogeneous technologies integration was addressed during the opening keynote and was a topic covered in many talks, mine were no exception.</p>

<p>I presented two talks: <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/cirpo/don-t-screw-it-up-how-to-build-durable-api">&ldquo;Don&rsquo;t screw it up! How to build durable API&rdquo;</a> and <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/cirpo/php-is-the-king-nodejs-is-the-prince-and-lua-is-the-fool">&ldquo;PHP is the king, nodejs the prince and Lua the fool&rdquo;</a>.</p>

<p>Both talks are based on the experience at Namshi, building our current service oriented architecture and API and how our stack is evolving.</p>

<iframe src="http://namshi.github.io//www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/40808376" width="425" height="355" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no" style="border:1px solid #CCC; border-width:1px; margin-bottom:5px; max-width: 100%;" allowfullscreen> </iframe>


<p> <div style="margin-bottom:5px"> </div></p>

<iframe src="http://namshi.github.io//www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/40818800" width="425" height="355" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no" style="border:1px solid #CCC; border-width:1px; margin-bottom:5px; max-width: 100%;" allowfullscreen> </iframe>


<p> <div style="margin-bottom:5px">  </div></p>

<p>At Namshi we believe that attending conferences and meetups is a very important as that helps the team and the individual developers grow.
It&rsquo;s a great opportunity to understand what&rsquo;s going on in our field and to meet other great developers.</p>

<p>What&rsquo;s next? If you&rsquo;re attending <a href="http://madrid2014.symfony.com/">SymfonyCon Madrid</a>, don&rsquo;t miss <a href="http://madrid2014.symfony.com/speakers">&ldquo;Hey, I just met AngularJS, and this is crazy, so here’s my JavaScript, let’s use it maybe&rdquo;</a> by <a href="http://tech.namshi.io/team/#Alessandro%20Nadalin">Alex</a>!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What went down at SymfonyLive London?]]></title>
    <link href="http://namshi.github.io/blog/2014/10/02/what-went-down-at-symfonylive-london/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-02T12:26:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://namshi.github.io/blog/2014/10/02/what-went-down-at-symfonylive-london</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/images/symfonylive.png" width="640" height="640" title="&lsquo;SymfonyLive&rsquo; &lsquo;SymfonyLive&rsquo;" >
SymfonyLive London 2014 concluded with top-notch presentations from Symfony and industry gurus. It was an exceptional
opportunity being able to attend this conference and meet those people.</p>

<p>Here is my summary about some of the talks I had the chance to attend:</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Keynote: Understanding Craftsmanship by <a href="https://twitter.com/_md">Marcello Duarte</a></h2>

<p>Marcello delivered an outstanding keynote presentation on achieving craftsmanship in software.
He provided a walk through the <a href="http://manifesto.softwarecraftsmanship.org/">Software Craftsmanship Manifesto</a>
and how the Agile methodology should have been evolved to consider software craftsmanship as one of its practices.</p>

<p>The talk focused on:</p>

<ul>
<li>Delivering a well crafted software by following good practices such as clean code</li>
<li>Being steadfast by considering yourself a craftsman rather than an executionar</li>
<li>Focusing on the community by having mentors and supporting other programmers</li>
<li>Enhancing productivity by dealing with customers as partners who understand your passion and approach
in delivering code rather than focusing on completing tasks</li>
</ul>


<iframe src="http://namshi.github.io//www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/39722355" width="427" height="356" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no" style="border:1px solid #CCC; border-width:1px; margin-bottom:5px; max-width: 100%;" allowfullscreen> </iframe>


<p> <div style="margin-bottom:5px"> <strong> <a href="https://www.slideshare.net/marcello.duarte/understanding-craftsmanship" title="Understanding craftsmanship" target="_blank">Understanding craftsmanship</a> </strong> from <strong><a href="http://www.slideshare.net/marcello.duarte" target="_blank">Marcello Duarte</a></strong> </div></p>

<h2>The dependency Trap by <a href="https://twitter.com/jakub_zalas">Jakub Zalas</a></h2>

<p>Jakub explained how bad it can be having a number of services depend on one external service and at a certain point,
when that external service needs to be replaced, you fall into what is called &lsquo;The Dependency Trap&rsquo; due
to high coupling.</p>

<p>The approach to follow in order to avoid such situations is to work on making internal services
loosely coupled from external ones by introducing interfaces and &lsquo;Dependency Inversion&rsquo;. The guidelines
of the Dependency Inversion principal are:</p>

<ul>
<li>High level modules (your services) should not depend on low level ones (libraries) instead, they should
depend on abstractions. In other words, both your services and the library should depend on interfaces that clearly
describe what they are expected to accomplish.</li>
<li>Abstractions should not depend on details. This means that your interface should not be a detail in a possible
more generic interface.</li>
</ul>


<p>Here at Namshi, we are introducing these practices, and as a starting point, we are loosely coupling our services from doctrine. It is
amazing to notice that we are on the right track and addressing industry wide issues!</p>

<h2>The Naked Bundle by <a href="https://twitter.com/matthiasnoback">Matthias Noback</a></h2>

<p>This was one of the most contreversial talks at the confrence! Matthias&rsquo;s goal through this talk was to motivate the symfony
community to start considering the fact that one day, they will be faced with a situation where they have to port their
code to a different framework. Motivated by that fact, he started exploring ways that allow a Symfony2 based codebase to be easily portable
to other frameworks and thus, depend less on the Symfony2 framework itself. Now the good part is that most of Symfony is based on components, however,
Bundles are not. He moves on by trying to introduce workarounds for controllers, entities and templates to reside outside the bundle and create the
&lsquo;Naked Bundle&rsquo;.</p>

<h2>Sylius e-commerce for symfony2 developers by Pawel Jedrzejewski</h2>

<p>A walk through Sylius, a powerful Symfony2 based E-commerce platform. Pawel explained how to start with Sylius, the available
bundles and components it introduces and how it can be used in non-Symfony codebase.</p>

<h2>Decoupling with design patterns and symfony DIC by <a href="https://twitter.com/everzet">Konstantin Kudryashov (everzet)</a></h2>

<p>One of the best presentations that took place at SymfonyLive, Everzet just rocked it! He introduced the techniques he
followed in building Behat v.3. His main goal was to try and deliver the most extensible test framework while
maintaining backword compatibility. He used these goals and techniques as examples on how Symfony2 based projects
should be built.</p>

<p>The main guidelines to achieve decoupling, extensibilty and backword compatibility are to:</p>

<ul>
<li>Avoid premature abstractions.</li>
<li>Close your code for any extensions (by using private attributes and final classes, for example).</li>
<li>When a use case that requires opening up a class or an attribute rises, identify a proper extension point and put lots of thought in it.</li>
<li>Whenever opening up a class or an attribute, keep in mind backward compatibility.</li>
<li>Utilize the Gang of Four design patterns wherever needed!</li>
</ul>


<p>In case of Behat, achieving the framework design goals was done by leveraging compiler passes as extension points and
using Delegation Loop, Decorator, Observer, Compsite, Chain of Responsibility and Adapter patterns. Each pattern was
used wherever necessary, for example, the Adapther pattern achieved the goal of backword compatibility by executing the
required transformation on legacy input and &lsquo;adapt&rsquo; it to the new one.</p>

<p>Basically, the solution to a desing problem must reside in one of the design patterns in the Gang of Four!</p>

<iframe src="http://namshi.github.io//www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/39591398" width="427" height="356" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no" style="border:1px solid #CCC; border-width:1px; margin-bottom:5px; max-width: 100%;" allowfullscreen> </iframe>


<p> <div style="margin-bottom:5px"> <strong> <a href="https://www.slideshare.net/everzet/decoupling-with-design-patterns-and-symfony2-dic" title="Decoupling with Design Patterns and Symfony2 DIC" target="_blank">Decoupling with Design Patterns and Symfony2 DIC</a> </strong> from <strong><a href="http://www.slideshare.net/everzet" target="_blank">Konstantin Kudryashov</a></strong> </div></p>

<h2>Keynote: Doing Everything With Nothing, Ephemeralization In The Cloud by <a href="https://twitter.com/dzuelke">David Zuelke</a></h2>

<p>A very inspiring talk by David, he walks through the history of the evolution of daily life tools and how they keep doing
more with less (Ephemeralization).
From that point onwords, he explains how this observation relates to the computing world. We see that the cloud is
evolving daily by intorducing enhancements that makes developers' life easier and making them focus on what is important to them.
Infrastructure-as-a-service (IaaS) and Platform-as-a-Service (PaaS) are examples of this evolution. He moves on by introducing heroku,
a PaaS, and how it contributes to this fact by providing out of the box system solutions to developers.</p>

<p>All in all, the talks were inspiring and addressed current issues in web development. Can&rsquo;t wait for SymfonyLive London 2015!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Design, Architecture and Code on the edge @Confoo]]></title>
    <link href="http://namshi.github.io/blog/2014/09/22/coding-on-the-edge-at-confoo/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-22T09:01:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://namshi.github.io/blog/2014/09/22/coding-on-the-edge-at-confoo</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>At Namshi we run a product that needs to evolve quickly and be ready to change: new features and
technologies are integrated every week to be able to keep up to date with the market and the technology around us.
That&rsquo;s how we started using nodejs, Angular, Docker, SPDY and much more&hellip;</p>

<p><strong>Do you want to hear more?</strong></p>

<!-- more -->


<p><img class="left team" src="/images/alex.jpg">
<a href="http://tech.namshi.io/team#Alessandro%20Nadalin">Alex</a> submitted a bunch of talks to the 2015 edition of the Confoo conference, so just
<a href="http://confoo.ca/en/call-for-papers/speaker/alessandro-nadalin">vote for his talks</a>.<br>
His talks cover a wide variety of topics from Symfony, Angular, HTTP to Dockerinzing your application.</p>

<p>How cool is that?<br>
If you are looking for sharp and engaging sessions, <strong>these are definitely bound to make you sit up and notice</strong>.</p>

<br>


<br>


<br>



]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
