<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: cybersecurity | Tech @ Namshi.com]]></title>
  <link href="http://namshi.github.io/blog/categories/cybersecurity/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://namshi.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2019-01-20T14:06:43+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://namshi.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Namshi]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Currently hiring: a CyberSecurity engineer]]></title>
    <link href="http://namshi.github.io/blog/2018/07/04/currently-hiring-a-cybersecurity-engineer/"/>
    <updated>2018-07-04T06:28:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://namshi.github.io/blog/2018/07/04/currently-hiring-a-cybersecurity-engineer</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Love penetration testing, DefCon, bug bounty programs and scrapping through lines
of code to find vulnerabilities? Then we might have the right opening for you!</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Here at Namshi we&rsquo;re committed to continuously improve our security posture, by
either <a href="/blog/2018/05/16/introducing-the-namshi-bug-bounty-program/">collaborating with security researchers across the globe</a> or with in-house expertise.</p>

<p>With this in mind, we would like to hire a security researcher that can help
us from this perspective: we see security as being a topic that will only gain additional
importance as time goes by, and we&rsquo;re committed to dedicating the right amount of time,
and money, to the cause :)</p>

<p>As a <strong>Security Engineer</strong>, you&rsquo;ll be tasked with running internal assessments, ranging
from <em>pentesting</em> our cloud infrastructure to social engineering around the office,
review our security policies and define the best strategy to improve our posture.
In addition to that, you will be actively collaborating with external researchers
through our HackerOne program, which is going to be directly under your responsibility.
On top of this, as the months will go by, you will probably spend time training
both our technical and non-technical staff to raise awareness and make sure we
got the basics covered.</p>

<p>Been into it since Kali was Backtrack? Spend time going through public bounty programs
to hack your way to a reward? Want to take on the responsibility of shaping Namshi&rsquo;s
defense? Then we’re definitely a match!</p>

<h2>Apply now!</h2>

<p>What are you waiting for? Send your application to <code>work-in-tech@namshi.com</code> and
let&rsquo;s have a chat!</p>

<p>P.S. A few months back I wrote a small piece about <a href="/blog/2016/12/06/get-that-job-at-namshi/">Namshi&rsquo;s hiring process and <em>desiderata</em></a>,
give it a look!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
